<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" version="3.3.0" xml:id="Stanbury-Pearl-Export-03-Intro-tei">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <author>Stanbury, Sarah</author>
        <sponsor>The University of Rochester</sponsor>
        <sponsor>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</sponsor>
        <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
        <funder>The University of Rochester</funder>
        <funder>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Amster, Mara I.</persName>
          <resp>Prepared edition for publication</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Conrath, Ryan</persName>
          <resp>Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp>Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Delcourt, Steffi</persName>
          <resp from="2025-04" to="2025-05">Audited documents prior to print/export</resp>
          <resp from="2025-04" to="2025-04">Collected metadata</resp>
          <resp from="2025-01" to="2025-02">Copyedited and proofread</resp>
          <resp from="2025-04" to="2025-05">Encoded TEI</resp>
          <resp from="2025-04" to="2025-04">Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp>
          <resp from="2025-01" to="2025-04">Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp from="2025-01" to="2025-02">Entered corrections for print edition</resp>
          <resp from="2025-01" to="2025-02">Formatted for print edition</resp>
          <resp from="2025-01" to="2025-04">Formatted for XML export</resp>
          <resp from="2025-05" to="2025-05">Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Johnson-Olin, Martha M.</persName>
          <resp>Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp>Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Kephart, Daniel</persName>
          <resp from="2024-02" to="2024-02">Collected metadata</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Lupack, Alan</persName>
          <resp>Copyedited and proofread</resp>
          <resp>Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp>
          <resp>Reviewed edition for consistency and audience</resp>
          <resp>Reviewed edition for content and scholarship</resp>
          <resp>Wrote reader report</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>McShane, Kara L.</persName>
          <resp>Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp>Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Peck, Russell A.</persName>
          <resp>Copyedited and proofread</resp>
          <resp>Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp>
          <resp>Reviewed edition for consistency and audience</resp>
          <resp>Reviewed edition for content and scholarship</resp>
          <resp>Wrote reader report</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Roth, Aaron</persName>
          <resp>Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp>Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Symons, Dana M.</persName>
          <resp>Prepared edition for publication</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Encoded in TEI in 2025.</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Rossell Hope Robbins Library, University of Rochester</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>https://www.library.rochester.edu/spaces/robbins</addrLine>
        </address>
        <publisher>The Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>https://www.sas.rochester.edu/eng/</addrLine>
        </address>
        <publisher>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>https://teams-medieval.org/about/</addrLine>
        </address>
        <distributor>The Rossell Hope Robbins Library, University of Rochester</distributor>
        <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>https://www.library.rochester.edu/spaces/robbins</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Downloading shall be restricted to one copy for private use.</p>
        </availability>
        <date/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="s">The Middle English Text Series</title>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Mara I. Amster</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Rita Copeland</persName>
          <orgName>University of Pennsylvania</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Thomas G. Hahn</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Lisa J. Kiser</persName>
          <orgName>Ohio State University</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Alan Lupack</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Associate Editor, Editorial Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Russell A. Peck</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>General Editor, Editorial Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Thomas H. Seiler</persName>
          <orgName>Western Michigan University</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>R. A. Shoaf</persName>
          <orgName>University of Florida</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>John William Sutton</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Dana M. Symons</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Assistant Editor, Editorial Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Bonnie Wheeler</persName>
          <orgName>Southern Methodist University</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>Unknown</author>
            <editor>Stanbury, Sarah</editor>
            <title>Pearl</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Medieval Institute Publications</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Kalamazoo, MI</pubPlace>
              <date>2001</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Middle English Texts Series offers a diverse and representative array of literary
          texts that medieval readers in the present-day British Isles would have encountered
          between the twelfth and sixteenth centuries. It is committed to making available both
          affordable print and open access editions to scholars, teachers, and students of the
          Western Middle Ages. In its digital publications, the series prioritizes a user-friendly
          interface and viewing options, multiple downloadable formats, enhanced searchability and
          filtering, and accessibility to the widest possible range of users.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>METS takes as its mission the creation of affordable editions that would pass scrutiny
          from the most demanding expert, yet would prove comprehensible, and even enticing, to
          someone who had never read Middle English before. This agenda dictates that METS
          publications offer not a critical edition reflecting all surviving manuscripts, and
          certainly not a diplomatic edition, but a best-text edition, informed by the notes and
          apparatus of earlier editions (where these exist), and by substantive variants from other
          manuscript witnesses. Transcriptions of Middle English texts are lightly modernized to
          ensure a smooth reading experience, while non-English texts preserve both the original
          language and a modern English translation in facing-page format. Each edition offers
          expert assistance with language and lexicon, providing glosses alongside the text(s),
          textual and explanatory notes, elucidation of unfamiliar contexts and traditions, and
          thematic and interpretive possibilities. All editions feature general introductions that
          set the edited text within its own time, place, and traditions, and link it to ancestor,
          congener, and successor materials. All publications contain comprehensive, current
          bibliographies of pertinent scholarship and criticism. House style is adapted from the <hi
            rend="italic">Chicago Manual of Style</hi>.</p>
        <correction>
          <p>This text may include corrections made after the original edition went to press in
            order to correct errors and improve glosses. For a full list of editorial and
            typographical corrections made to this edition, please view its correction log on
            Github:
            https://github.com/mets-editions/stanbury-pearl/blob/main/stanbury-pearl-export-corrections-log.docx</p>
        </correction>
      </editorialDecl>
      <schemaRef url="https://metseditions.org/schema/mets-editions.xsd"/>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English, Modern (1500-present)</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>First edition published in 2001</change>
      <change>Encoded in HTML</change>
      <change>Entered editorial corrections in 2025</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
      <anchor xml:id="Stanbury-Pearl-Export-03-Intro"/>
      <div type="text">
        <p style="bodyfirst" n="1">The poem known as <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> was written in
          England in the fourteenth century. It exists today in a small vellum manuscript, one of
          the treasures of the British Library, MS Cotton Nero A.x., as the first of four poems
          copied by a single scribe. Following <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> are three more
          alliterative narratives, two of them, <hi rend="italic">Patience</hi> and <hi
            rend="italic">Cleanness</hi>, retellings of Old Testament stories, and the last the
          Arthurian masterpiece, <hi rend="italic">Sir Gawain and the Green Knight</hi>. All four
          poems were probably written by the same poet, but who that poet was remains a mystery, as
          indeed does much of the manuscript’s history. There is little surprising about the absence
          of an author’s name attached to one or all of these poems; until the fifteenth century and
          later, writers working in English seldom signed their work. English was perhaps deemed too
          common and “vernacular” to bear claiming in a world where French had remained the lingua
          franca of international courtly business and of English high culture since the time of the
          Norman conquest. What is more surprising is the apparent marginalization of these
          sophisticated and exuberant poems. To gauge the popularity of a text in a pre-print
          culture, we can often use the number of surviving manuscripts as a general guide. For <hi
            rend="italic">Pearl</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Patience</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
            >Cleanness</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Sir Gawain and the Green Knight</hi>, there
          remains only the one in which they have survived together. To gain a sense of a work’s
          importance in its own time we can also pay attention to its critical legacy, the responses
          of contemporaries and followers, for popular narratives intercalate richly with other
          texts as writers read and borrow from each other. For the texts in the <hi rend="italic"
            >Pearl</hi> manuscript there exist only the vaguest of echoes in later writings to
          suggest that they were read or known at all. Yet these poems rank with the works of
          Chaucer and Langland for wit, virtuosity with language and prosody, learnedness, and sheer
          skill in telling a story.</p>
        <p style="body" n="1"><hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>, the first poem in the manuscript, leads
          off with a rich display of these qualities in a story of crossing-over, the stepping out
          from the ordinary life into a parallel universe where things operate by different natural
          laws: down the rabbit hole, through the wardrobe or looking glass, across the ocean to be
          shipwrecked on Prospero’s island or, more recently, across a bridge to the island of
          Willow Springs in Gloria Naylor’s haunting novel, <hi rend="italic">Mama Day</hi>, where
          the crossing-over moves into a place of memory and hope, the nostalgic space of home as
          well as Beulah or Eden, the earthly paradise. If <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> resists
          identification by author, date, occasion, or place of composition, it can be localized by
          its conversation with other stories of crossing-over, which most often take the form in
          the Middle Ages of dream visions, stories of transport that occur when the figure telling
          the story falls asleep. As a narrative structure, the dream vision claims a deep heritage
          in some of the most widely read vernacular texts of western European culture. The Italian
            <hi rend="italic">Divine </hi><hi rend="italic">Comedy</hi> by Dante and the French <hi
            rend="italic">Roman de la Rose</hi>, begun by Guillaume de Lorris and continued by Jean
          de Meun, both seem to have been read and known by the author of <hi rend="italic"
            >Pearl</hi>. The use of the dream as a narrative point of departure also structures the
          English <hi rend="italic">Piers </hi><hi rend="italic">Plowman</hi> by William Langland
          and the four great dream visions by Geoffrey Chaucer. What these narratives share — and
          indeed, what it may be said that all stories of crossing-over share — is a place of
          possibility, where the narrative begins with a sense of being stuck or even trapped and
          then moves into a place of freedom or expansiveness. In his dream the narrator of <hi
            rend="italic">Pearl</hi> slips into an “aventure,” which means “marvel” or “quest” (line
          64). Dante at the opening of <hi rend="italic">Inferno</hi> is trapped in a dark wood, in
          the middle of his life, but in his vision becomes a traveler in time and space, circling
          down through hell and then climbing up to a vision of paradise. Harry Potter is virtually
          a prisoner of the Dursleys, but transposed to Hogwarts, he is the airborne star of
          quidditch.</p>
        <p style="body" n="2"><hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> similarly opens in a setting that
          emphasizes limits: “clos,” meaning “set” or “enclosed,” is a key word of the second line.
          In its staging of a dream vision, <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> is explicitly situated
          within a courtly and aristocratic world; and indeed, the poem in many respects takes its
          shape and particular power from the interplay between a courtly habitus, a place of money,
          judgment, pleasures, and rules of behavior, and the uncanny yet familiar space of the
          crossing-over. Beginning with a precious object, the poem also opens with attention to
          location and surveillance, set in motion through acts of judgment in familiar kinds of
          spaces. The jeweler/narrator looks at and judges gems in general; he has one in particular
          in a splendid setting, so “clanly clos” (line 2), but it falls from him and disappears
          into the ground; his “[a]llas” (line 9) precipitates the poem backwards into the past
          through a memory of loss.</p>
        <p style="body" n="3">The poem takes off from this point of departure as a story of loss and
          a quest, opening as well in a space that can only move outward from containment: the pearl
          in a setting, the earth into which the pearl disappears, the garden into which the
          narrator enters to grieve it. Following the narrator’s swoon in the garden, he finds
          himself in a landscape peculiarly transformed into a place of natural delights, evocative
          of accounts of the earthly paradise and also of the sensuous love gardens that appear so
          frequently in medieval literature. In this sinuous Eden he forgets what he has lost. He
          follows a stream and enjoys the pleasures of the senses — fragrances of flowers and fruit,
          birdsong, the light through the leaves. Soon, however, he is literally brought up short
          when he sees a young woman standing on the other side of the brook. Dressed all in white,
          with a large pearl in the middle of her breast, she is disturbingly familiar. He asks her
          if she is his lost pearl, a question that she evades as she points to his faulty logic in
          saying that she is lost. From this point the story moves into a dialogue. In a passionate
          interrogation the narrator struggles to place her within known frames of reference and
          even to reclaim her: how can she be lost (dead) and found? Now that he has found her
          again, how can he give her up? Where does she live? How can she, who lived “not two yer”
          (line 483) in our land, be a queen in heaven? To his questions she responds with answers
          that are both learned and measured, and occasionally even disciplinary, meeting the rage
          of his questions with cool theological puzzles: he cannot understand the divide between
          them because she has moved to a place that operates by an apparently different set of laws
          — and whose operations form the intellectual substance of her replies. To his questions
          about where she lives, she promises him a sight of her home, and finally leads him to a
          vision of a beautiful city, the New Jerusalem, where she lives as a bride of the Lamb.
          This forms the final location of the vision, a visionary chthonic moment that moves him to
          try to cross the stream. It is at that point that he wakes up, and the poem ends.</p>
        <p style="heading" n="1">Metaphor and Form</p>
        <p style="bodyfirst" n="2">In the great dream vision stories of the Middle Ages, the drama
          of the other-world adventure is made explicitly homely or familiar through use of a
          first-person narrator, and one who conventionally falls into certain categories of
          “ordinariness”: he is foolish or middle-aged, or overtired, or sad. The use of a
          first-person voice, coupled with techniques of familiarization, make it easy to assume the
          narrator’s persona and go along for the ride. In <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> that
          assumption or costuming in the narrator’s identity quickly plays into a story of troubled
          equivalence, since from the first word we get it wrong; what we take as a pearl, we soon
          find out, is more than a pearl. The pearl is a metaphor whose various meanings, unfolding
          as the story progresses, are subject to repeated reassessment. Paul Ricoeur speaks of
          metaphor as a “planned category mistake” in which linguistic limits and categories are
          willfully broken to engage new possibilities: “the power of metaphor would be to break an
          old categorization, in order to establish new logical frontiers on the ruins of their
            forerunners.”<note target="#1" type="footnotelink">1</note> Metaphor, that is, forces a
          reevaluation of assumed truths: things may be as they seem, but are also more than they
          seem. As it takes on narrative form, ordering a set of meanings over and beyond the
          literal, metaphor becomes allegory. In medieval dream visions, most of them allegories, we
          are particularly aware of the divide between things in their essences or “object-hoods”
          and the contingencies of value and desire that circulate about them. Even as the naïve
          wanderer in the dream vision encounters a cyber world, rich and strange, the living body
          of the narrator is always present at the margins of the story, asleep in a swoon, however
          much we forget him or her (in medieval vision literature, invariably him) — and is a
          reminder that things operate according to familiar physical laws.</p>
        <p style="body" n="4"><hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> mobilizes a set of “calculated category
          mistakes” through the responses of both the reader and the narrator, and also through an
          extraordinarily rich set of changes rung on language throughout the poem. Both narrator
          and reader engage in acts of misreading and misinterpretation; and, in fact, the
          narrator’s acts of passionate misreading structure the dialogue with the <hi rend="italic"
            >Pearl</hi>-maiden, which takes the form of a quiz in which he repeatedly tries to
          categorize her within known and familiar frames of reference — a set of collisions, we
          could argue, that pit the familiar surround of courtly culture, the narrator’s ambit,
          against the scriptural stories and visions that the maiden lays out in the answers — that
          sets allegorical “truths” with particular abruptness against sense perception. We begin
          with the loss of a pearl in a garden; that pearl, we find out, is also a girl, the
          narrator’s two-year-old daughter; it is also the kingdom of heaven described in Matthew
          14:45–46: “the kingdom of heaven is like the merchant seeking valuable pearls, who, when
          he had found a pearl of great price, went and sold all that he had, and bought it.” <hi
            rend="italic">Pearl</hi> sets in motion a set of “category mistakes” that comment
          uneasily on the very nature of categories: what is a pearl? What is a girl? How do we know
          or evaluate what we see? What are the bases of aristocratic identity and affinity?</p>
        <p style="body" n="5">One of the particular achievements of <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>
          lies in its overlay of a linear narrative with a set of metaphoric registers that with
          extraordinary facility rewrites the definitions of the poem’s central terms. That which
          appears fixed, stable, and known is not: like the pearl itself, which slips away to
          transform into something else, words recur throughout the poem with new meanings. The
          economy of metaphor, or rather its hyper-economy, lies in its uncanny ability to express
          both equivalence and multiplicity; ostensibly an equation of identity, marked by an equal
          sign, metaphor also adds up to the sum of its parts.<note target="#2" type="footnotelink"
            >2</note> The pearl <hi rend="italic">is</hi> a gem, <hi rend="italic">is</hi> a
          two-year old child, <hi rend="italic">is</hi> a beautiful young woman, <hi rend="italic"
            >is</hi> the immortal soul, <hi rend="italic">is</hi> the heavenly city — as well as a
          collective of the properties that inhere to each term singly. The language of <hi
            rend="italic">Pearl</hi> is unusually rich in the double entendre, also a form of
          metaphor, particularly in terms for judgment and evaluation.<note target="#3"
            type="footnotelink">3</note> Indeed, <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> uses a dizzying
          punnology, embedded within concepts, words and grammatical structures and even within the
          system of its meter and rhyme,<note target="#4" type="footnotelink">4</note> as if in
          invitation to engage with language as an encounter with haunting and repetition. In the
          first set of stanzas, the stanza-group in which the narrator returns to the place or spot
          where his pearl — née daughter — was lost, “spot” recurs in ways that force associative
          relationships between location and absence, between the set of compass points that places
          him physically and the negativity that marks the pearl as both without stain (without
          “spot”) and without a place (without “spot”) in his world. In this elegy, the instability
          of language recapitulates or, we might say, performs the poem’s story of bereavement.
          Language itself tells us all we need to know about loss.</p>
        <p style="body" n="6">Integral to the poem’s play with language are formal patternings that
          build repetition and change into the structure of the poem. In its principles of rhyme,
          versification, and numbering, <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> is unmatched for complexity in
          Middle English poetry and perhaps rivaled only by Dante’s <hi rend="italic">Divine</hi><hi
            rend="italic"> Comedy</hi>. Attention to number is a vital part of the poem’s design.
          The use of a twelve-line stanza seems to be carefully chosen as part of a numerological
          structure: the New Jerusalem has twelve tiers in its foundation and is also twelve
          furlongs long; the poem itself, 1212 lines long, is a composite of twelves. Concepts of
          perfection and blemish parlayed through the image of the pearl are also graphed through
          number. Comprising twenty sets of five, the stanzas are grouped to add up to 100, a number
          of perfection. This symmetry is offset, however, by the curious addition of an extra
          stanza in the fifteenth set — with the result that the stanzas total 101. One hundred and
          one, a strong number that suggests new beginning after return, is doubtless no accident.
          This number appears as a stanza or chapter total in several other medieval texts; and most
          strikingly, 101 is also the sum of the stanzas of the Cotton Nero A.x. manuscript’s most
          famous poem, <hi rend="italic">Sir Gawain and the Green Knight</hi>.<note target="#5"
            type="footnotelink">5</note></p>
        <p style="body" n="7">Repetition and change also structure the prosodic form of <hi
            rend="italic">Pearl</hi> to an unusual degree. The stanzas themselves follow a tight
          rhyme scheme, with three sets of rhyme appearing in each: ababababbcbc. In stanza form,
            <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> shares many affinities with French, Italian, and Latin
          fourteenth-century poems as well as with other lyrics in English from the late thirteenth
          century through the early fifteenth century. In its use of heavy alliteration and a
          complex stanza form <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> bears some similarities to the lyrics
          from MS Harley 2253, c. 1340. In prosodic form, however, it shares closer affinities with
          later poems. <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>’s use of a refrain and a twelve-line form of the
          ballade or pseudo-ballade stanza link it with a continental form that first appeared in
          English with lyrics by Chaucer, c. 1380, and that is used in several of the lyrics in the
          Vernon manuscript (c. 1390).<note target="#6" type="footnotelink">6</note>
          <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>’s stanza moves with a rippling kind of musicality: two rhyme
          words alternate until the final four lines, which often work as a quatrain, where one of
          the rhymes continues, and a new counterpoint is picked up. Rhyme moves the poem in
          increments of repetition and change. As Marie Borroff describes the effect of rhyme in the
          ballade stanza, it is “like a series of shifts to the next higher musical key in
          successive choruses of a popular song.”<note target="#7" type="footnotelink">7</note></p>
        <p style="body" n="8">Where <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> departs from English and
          continental forms of the ballade, however, is in its use of an intricate system of verbal
          echoes. While a refrain and verbal repetition are common features of late medieval lyrics,
          both English and continental, <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> transforms the refrain into an
          echoic play of concatenation. Not only do the five stanzas in each stanza-group share a
          repeating last word and often entire line, but stanzas are also linked together by
          repetition of the last word of the refrain of one stanza in the first line of the next, an
          echoic effect that strings stanzas together like pearls on a necklace. <hi rend="italic"
            >Pearl</hi>’s mathematically precise system of stanza numbering and its uses of
          repetition and verbal linking produce a poem that is crafted with unusual care, the poem
          itself as a kind of precious object. At the same time, however, repetition of its
          link-words also allows an unusual latitude and play with the possibilities of meaning. In
          each stanza within a stanza-group the final word is always the same, but the line in which
          that word is embedded is not, so meaning can vary by syntax as well as by the play of
          lexical possibilities within words themselves. Far from restricting or confining meaning,
            <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>’s elaborate form allows the fullest play of its punnology.
          Words may repeat and return, but return as altered bearers of meaning.</p>
        <p style="body" n="9">The experience of reading <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> can thus be
          unsettling, for while the story, as a narrative, appears to proceed in a sequential or
          linear way, the multiple meanings that radiate out from central terms, and the shifts in
          its categories that displace from its central image, are far less clear, particularly in
          the hallucinatory transformation of the pearl to the beautiful young woman who herself is
          understood to represent a two-year-old child, presumably the narrator’s daughter. Yet at
          the same time that language and prosody enact processes of transformation on the pearl,
          and even theological possibilities of post-mortem transfiguration, its central metaphor
          never departs fully from its primary identity: the pearl is a pearl. Writing of the
          curious materiality of metaphor, Darrel Mansell locates the impulse to metaphor in a
          desire to ground language in objects, an impulse he assigns to a yearning for a mythic
          lost time of pre-linguistic plenitude when things were as they seemed: in metaphor, which
          is always a surplus, “the original world of matter is glimpsed still almost innocent of
            predication.”<note target="#8" type="footnotelink">8</note> In <hi rend="italic"
            >Pearl</hi>, language and image never abandon the materiality of their metaphoric point
          of departure. <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>, that is, continues to be the word/name that
          the narrator utters when addressing the maiden. Pearls appear throughout the transformed
          landscape of the crossed-over world: in the gems gleaming in the river, in the clothing of
          the maiden and indeed in the very whiteness of her skin, on the gates of the New
          Jerusalem, and, metaphorically, in the pearly fleece of the Lamb.</p>
        <p style="body" n="10">This material grounding in pearls points to a question: is pearl
          afferent or referent? Signifier or signified? While the pearl is of course a symbol for
          the evanescent or the spiritual, the child and/or immortal soul, and the narrator’s search
          for the pearl an allegory for a spiritual search, the pearl lends the poem a peculiar
          materiality and presence; it is not just a point of departure. In his study of the elegy
          Peter Sacks writes of the ways that elegiac poetry grounds itself repetitively, indeed
          obsessively, in objects, replaying in poetry and in language the central trauma of loss,
          Freud’s <hi rend="italic">fort</hi>/<hi rend="italic">da</hi>. The elegy, Sacks writes, is
          hauntingly recapitulative in impulse and form, replaying a series of losses that looks
          back to an originary trauma, the primal separation from maternal plenitude.<note
            target="#9" type="footnotelink">9</note> Language in elegy is unusually concretized,
          Sacks argues, and in <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> we can perhaps see how the poem’s
          central metaphor or object also enacts this material requirement.<note target="#10"
            type="footnotelink">10</note> The poem offers consolation through the maiden’s discourse
          on the delights of heaven, but perhaps an even deeper consolation in the visual promise
          that that which is lost, the pearl, does not go away.</p>
        <p style="heading" n="2">Contexts: Date, Authorship, Occasion</p>
        <p style="bodyfirst" n="3">To this point I have been concerned with the poem’s uses of words
          and of techniques of prosody as tools skillfully deployed to produce emotional and
          aesthetic effects — and effects, as we shall see, that are also ethically and politically
          charged. The poem’s uses of language and of images, and especially the pearl, can also
          help to localize a possible time, place, and occasion for its composition. Efforts to
          identify a date and occasion of composition and an author for the poems of the <hi
            rend="italic">Pearl</hi> manuscript, indeed, have occupied the attention of numerous
          scholars in the last century. <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>, along with <hi rend="italic"
            >Patience</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Cleanness</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Sir Gawain and
            </hi><hi rend="italic">the Green Knight</hi>, is remarkably evasive on matters that
          could identify a time and place of its composition, such as names of living people, real
          places, or current events, a feature of all four poems that Charles Muscatine has
          speculated is a form of escapism or reaction through “allegiance to high-medieval
            feudalism.”<note target="#11" type="footnotelink">11</note> Some evidence for localizing
          the manuscript is provided by dialect, which has been identified as Northwest Midlands.
          Both text and manuscript have been localized to Cheshire, with a recent study by Hoyt
          Duggan placing the poet’s natal dialect in Staffordshire and the scribe somewhat more
            northerly.<note target="#12" type="footnotelink">12</note> The dialect of the poems is
          difficult for most speakers of English today, for standard modern English has descended
          not from the Cheshire dialect of the Northwest Midlands but from London English, used by
          Chaucer and his London contemporaries. Although the dialect can locate the language of
          poet and scribe within a fairly precise isoglos, it does not necessarily identify the
          place of composition; and one question that has perplexed scholars is whether the poems
          are the product of a regional and provincial culture, or whether they could be at home in
          a much more central and urban location, or even the London court.<note target="#13"
            type="footnotelink">13</note> As for dating, language provides no clear evidence that
          can pinpoint the poems with precision, though one computer-based statistical study
          calibrating the percentages of words of Germanic, French, or Scandinavian origin indicates
          that the etymological mix of Cotton Nero A.x. is consistent with Middle English in
            1390.<note target="#14" type="footnotelink">14</note> Use of descriptive details in
          these poems for purposes of dating can be particularly slippery. One scholar has attempted
          to locate <hi rend="italic">Gawain</hi> in the mid-1300s on the basis of costume and
          armor; yet those details could well be the product of calculated invention to situate the
          poem in a somewhat earlier time.<note target="#15" type="footnotelink">15</note> In her
          study of <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> and the ballade form Susanna Fein argues for dating
            <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> in the mid-1380s, but that date may attempt to pinpoint its
          production somewhat too exactly.<note target="#16" type="footnotelink">16</note> As with
          language or details of place and costume, evidence from prosody can more securely suggest
          an earliest date rather than a final one, since a poet working somewhat later (1390s)
          could have chosen to work within a traditional form rather than attempt the latest thing.
          For fixed points regarding the production of these poems we have two dates that are quite
          widely separated in time. The earliest date must be 1348, the date for the founding of the
          order of the garter, whose motto, “honi soit qui mal pense,” appears as a coda to <hi
            rend="italic">Sir Gawain </hi><hi rend="italic">and the Green Knight</hi>. On
          paleographical evidence the <hi rend="italic">terminus ad </hi><hi rend="italic">quem</hi>
          must be c. 1400, the latest date for the composition of the manuscript.<note target="#17"
            type="footnotelink">17</note> While the question is by no means settled, recent research
          on the poems of the <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> manuscript, and especially <hi
            rend="italic">Gawain</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>, has tended to favor a late
          rather than an early date, in the 1380s or even the 1390s.</p>
        <p style="body" n="11">Authorship remains one of the prize questions about the poems of
          Cotton Nero A.x. Were the four poems contained in the <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>
          manuscript written by a single poet, and might that poet also have written <hi
            rend="italic">St. Erkenwald</hi>, a poem that has survived in a separate manuscript? <hi
            rend="italic">St. Erkenwald</hi>, an alliterative London poem in the Cheshire dialect,
          shares many features of language and imagery, and on that basis has been linked with the
            <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>-poet, though most readers now discount the connection.<note
            target="#18" type="footnotelink">18</note> The argument for linking the four poems in
          the Cotton Nero A.x. manuscript to a single author rests on a good deal of subjective
          criteria but also on certain features of the manuscript itself that give it an unusual
          integrity. It is the unique Middle English manuscript to contain only alliterative poems;
          it also contains illustrations, an unusual feature in a Middle English verse
            manuscript.<note target="#19" type="footnotelink">19</note> Dialect also argues in favor
          of common authorship, as do shared metrical and stylistic characteristics. Three are
          narratives written in an alliterative long line, and <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>, a
          metrically regular poem, also makes use of alliterative patterning. Less quantifiably, the
          poems share certain thematic preoccupations: all four repeatedly pressure questions of
          behavior, or what we might call modeling, how one “confourns” or conforms to ideals of
          courtly or Christian behavior, to use a word from <hi rend="italic">Cleanness</hi>. All
          four tell stories of crises in commensurating individual behavior with top-down or divine
          ordinances. All four present brilliantly visualized descriptions, particularly of nature,
          and make skilled and strategic uses of point of view. All four are “courtly.”<note
            target="#20" type="footnotelink">20</note></p>
        <p style="body" n="12">There is no firm evidence at all to suggest who might have written
          the poems, though numerous names have been put forth. The scholars who propose that <hi
            rend="italic">Pearl</hi> is an elegy written on the death of Margaret, daughter of John
          Hastings, Earl of Pembroke, also suggest that the poem was written by either John Prat or
          John Donne, both of them clerks of Pembroke.<note target="#21" type="footnotelink"
            >21</note> By far the candidate with the greatest longevity in the critical literature
          is Mascy or Massey. A spate of discussions has debated the possibility that the poems were
          written by a member of the Mascy family, a discussion initiated by linking the inscription
          “Hugo de” in the manuscript to the name “Masse” in <hi rend="italic">St. Erkenwald</hi>,
          producing “Hugo de Masse,” a name that can be connected to an important Cheshire family.
          Subsequent support for Mascy has drawn on a variety of cryptographic evidence, finding
          signatures hidden in the manuscript marginalia and encoded in the numbering and
            lettering.<note target="#22" type="footnotelink">22</note> The idea that <hi
            rend="italic">Pearl</hi>, in particular, could contain a cryptogram in its elaborate
          prosodic and mathematical structure is plausible. As I discuss below, some of the
          marguerite poems of Machaut and Froissart, with which <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> can
          perhaps be linked, hide the names of the poet and the poetic subject within cryptograms,
          as if to suggest that a hidden authorial signature is part of the game with metaphor.<note
            target="#23" type="footnotelink">23</note> Evidence from cryptography or other forms of
          textual and historical data has to date produced no consensus on the authorship of <hi
            rend="italic">Pearl</hi> or any of the poems in Cotton Nero A.x, although it has
          produced many assertions.</p>
        <p style="body" n="13">In considering the occasion for which <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>
          might have been written, the narrative form provides perhaps the most articulate evidence.
          Quite a few readers have approached <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> as a formal allegory or
          spiritual quest, a poem that details the soul’s progress, with the pearl as a symbol for
          certain bodily or spiritual qualities: purity or virginity; the soul; heaven.<note
            target="#24" type="footnotelink">24</note>
          <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> clearly is informed by mystical and devotional practices
          current in late fourteenth-century England. Yet <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>, in form an
          allegory, is above all an elegy, a poem written about the death of one who was beloved.
          Most early readers of <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> assumed that the poet was writing of
          the death of his own daughter, with the implication that the poem was written in an effort
          to “work through” his grief.<note target="#25" type="footnotelink">25</note> An
          understanding of the systems of text production in the Middle Ages within structures of
          patronage now would argue against identifying the author with the narrator, and suggest
          instead that the poem was more likely a commissioned work, probably written as a
          consolatory piece to commemorate the death of a daughter, and probably the daughter of an
          important magnate or member of the royal house. As a possible source or model for <hi
            rend="italic">Pearl</hi>, Boccaccio’s <hi rend="italic">Olympia</hi> is often mentioned,
          a poem in which a man named Silvio is granted a vision of Violante, his lost daughter,
          transformed and living as Olympia with the Virgin and Son on a paradisal mountain.<note
            target="#26" type="footnotelink">26</note> Although <hi rend="italic">Olympia</hi> and
            <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> bear some notable parallels, the form of Boccaccio’s poem
          as Latin eclogue and its classicizing allusions give it a markedly different tenor from
            <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>. Closer to <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> in form and feeling
          is Chaucer’s <hi rend="italic">Book of the Duchess</hi>, a dream vision elegy written on
          the occasion of the death of Blanche, wife of John of Gaunt. Names proposed for whom the
          poem could be commemorating include Margaret, granddaughter of Edward III,<note
            target="#27" type="footnotelink">27</note> and Anne of Bohemia.<note target="#28"
            type="footnotelink">28</note> Speculations on the occasion of the poem are not limited
          to elegy, however. Ian Bishop has suggested that the poem marks the initiation of an adult
          catechumen, or newly baptized person, and more recently Lynn Staley has suggested that the
          poem was composed to commemorate the entrance into a nunnery, a figurative death to the
          world, of an aristocratic child, and specifically Isabel, born in 1384 as third daughter
          of Thomas of Woodstock, one of the younger sons of Edward III.<note target="#29"
            type="footnotelink">29</note></p>
        <p style="heading" n="3">Courtly Economics and the Ricardian Court</p>
        <p style="bodyfirst" n="4">By identifying the narrator as a jeweler and the central image as
          a pearl, the poet seems to be writing with the values and possessions of the rich clearly
          in mind. The term jeweler can encompass not only a goldsmith or artisan but also a dealer
          in or even owner of gems or art objects, and hence the projected identity of the speaker
          could be entirely at home among an aristocratic audience.<note target="#30"
            type="footnotelink">30</note> The poem’s central image keeps the poem firmly grounded in
          a world of money and exchange, a world whose values and deluxe detailing are consonant
          with the cultural values and fittings of the fourteenth-century English court. If
          consolation is effected in part in the return of its repressed, the pearl, it is also
          effected in the certainty that the world in which the poem is “set” is also fixed and
          stable. “Paye,” the last word of the poem’s first line and also the link-word of the last
          stanza-group and, indeed, final word of the poem, bespeaks a set of comfortably transposed
          values, and values that are fully legible within idealized terms of monied exchange:
          “paye” in the first line refers to the judgment and pleasure of princes, who value pearls;
          “pay” in the last line refers to the reward and pleasures of heaven.<note target="#31"
            type="footnotelink">31</note> Indeed, the poem’s elaborate gemmology and interest in
          aristocratic values have led recent scholars to argue for dating it in the last years of
          the fourteenth century and specifically within the milieu of Richard II’s court. While
          these arguments are speculative, the circumstantial evidence is rich and tantalizing
          enough to merit summarizing here. Until recently the poem’s dialect has led scholars to
          assume that it was produced within a monastic establishment or baronial home in Cheshire,
          and probably by a learned cleric intimately familiar with the Bible and also well-versed
          in French and Italian poetry. Recent studies on the cultural and even manpower
          interchanges between Cheshire and the royal court have led to a reevaluation of this view.
          Michael Bennett has argued persuasively that the poet’s regional dialect does not limit
          the place of origin to a regional location. Richard II’s court was fully hospitable to
          arts patronage of the kind that would support the <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>-poet.
          Richard also surrounded himself with a large group of knights from Cheshire and elevated
          Cheshire to a region of prime importance: far from being an alien tongue, the dialect of
          the <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>-poet would have been fully at home in Richard’s court
            circles.<note target="#32" type="footnotelink">32</note> Perhaps a highly sophisticated
          and learned cleric, writing with the interests and tastes of a court in mind and au
          courant with the reading tastes of international high culture, the poet of <hi
            rend="italic">Pearl</hi> was above all a “courtier’s courtier.”<note target="#33"
            type="footnotelink">33</note></p>
        <p style="body" n="14">John Bowers has further argued for a set of parallels between the
          poem and the cultural life of Richard’s court, with particular attention to some of the
          poem’s more dramatic and vivid images, including the pearl, the lamb, and the New
            Jerusalem.<note target="#34" type="footnotelink">34</note> The remarkable detailing of
          ornament, the love of description as a kind of piling on of the deluxe, fits with
          particular consonance in Richard’s court, which was often cited and criticized for
          extravagance by contemporary chroniclers. Richard’s court was marked by its love of all
          things French, “a passion for jewelry in the court circles” and a love of aristocratic
            regalia.<note target="#35" type="footnotelink">35</note> Bowers, proposing a date for
            <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> in or around 1395, argues that <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>
          bespeaks Richard’s political aspirations, with the poem’s court of heaven as a visionary
          courtly body politic.<note target="#36" type="footnotelink">36</note> Both Bowers and
          Bennett have argued that the locus of the <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>-poet within Richard
          II’s court could also account for the demise and dramatic marginalization of this
          spectacular set of poems.<note target="#37" type="footnotelink">37</note> This scenario,
          while built on circumstantial evidence, provides a fascinating if hypothetical political
          backdrop for the manuscript’s history. The manuscript that survives, in single form, is
          doubtless a copy of an earlier exemplar, and an exemplar that perhaps was quite lavish.
          One scholar has argued, on the basis of scribal errors, that the surviving manuscript is
          at six or seven removes from the original version.<note target="#38" type="footnotelink"
            >38</note> With the ascendancy of Henry IV and the Lancastrians after Richard’s death or
          execution in 1399, the new court exacted a thorough repression of signs of the deposed
          king, extinguishing with particular thoroughness the Cheshire connection to promote London
          as the place of the new court, and of London English as the new language of the state. If
          the poems of the <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> manuscript were a product of the Ricardian
          court, they could well have suffered a similar erasure. Written in the Cheshire dialect,
          the manuscript of <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> might also have been the target of this
          systematic political repression and rewriting of the past.</p>
        <p style="body" n="15">Whether or not we situate <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> within Richard
          II’s court with the precision that Bowers and Bennett suggest, the poem certainly
          expresses many of the intellectual interests and aesthetic demands of an aristocratic
          milieu in the late fourteenth century — and an aristocratic milieu, it could be argued,
          that is at work to reconcile the pressures of the marketplace with both courtly and
          theological values. If the poem’s visible surface is constructed of precious objects, from
          the pearl to the gem-encrusted and gilded New Jerusalem, those surfaces are also
          repeatedly subjected to speculation about their value and operate in the poem within a
          complex commentary on measure, merit, quantification and valuation. In a recent study of
          market economics and scholastic theology in the fourteenth century, Joel Kaye argues that
          a “passion to measure,” which came to pervade every area of scholastic thinking in the
          fourteenth century, was directly influenced by the new monetization of the European
          marketplace. Rather than emerging solely from within intellectual debates within
          universities, the “measuring mania” of scholastic philosophy was directly influenced by
          interactions between gown and town; geometrical theorems of a new economics responded
          directly to daily transactions in the market squares in a dynamic interaction that, Kaye
          argues, was crucial to the development of scientific methodologies. Some of the most
          dramatic developments in new economic thinking in the fourteenth century, and particularly
          in geometry, concerned theories of equalization and commensurability, for money, like
          geometry, “commensurated the most seemingly in-commensurable goods and services.”<note
            target="#39" type="footnotelink">39</note></p>
        <p style="body" n="16">In <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>, with its intricate numerological
          structure, verbal concatenation, and complex rhyme, we certainly find evidence of a
          “measuring mania,” and indeed the poem could be described as a study in issues of relation
          — with language, in its rich metaphoricity and punnologies, itself a medium of exchange.
          The image of the pearl may itself situate the poem within a dialogue among late
          fourteenth-century poets on poetic composition, and particularly on the instability of
          language in a commensurate set of relationships. Another word for pearl is “margery,” from
          the French <hi rend="italic">marguerite</hi>, a term that is used to designate the pearl
          four times in the poem. Marguerite was a popular female name, given prominence, no doubt,
          by the tremendous vogue of St. Margaret in the late Middle Ages, and in French <hi
            rend="italic">marguerite</hi> was also the word for the daisy or heliotrope. In 1364
          Guillaume de Machaut, the popular French composer and poet, wrote the first of several
          “marguerite” poems, with the marguerite an allegorical daisy designating an actual woman,
          Marguerite of Flanders.<note target="#40" type="footnotelink">40</note> Following Machaut,
          marguerite poems, several of which take an allegorical daisy as an elaborate conceit to
          designate historical women, were also written in French by Machaut’s contemporaries, Jean
          Froissart and Eustache Deschamps, and in English by Chaucer. It seems quite possible that
          the poet of <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>, which also rings a set of changes between a
          “margery pearl” and a young girl or young woman, was familiar with at least some of these
          poems. In an essay on metaphor and the marguerite poems, Peter Travis has recently argued
          that the marguerite poems constitute an international dialogue of sorts among poets. In
          the marguerite poems, their practitioners were engaged in an exploration, through a
          metaphor, of the instability of language, or indeed, of the very workings of poetry.<note
            target="#41" type="footnotelink">41</note></p>
        <p style="body" n="17">The theology of <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>, played out in images
          and in the debate between the narrator and the maiden, also circles repeatedly around the
          problematics of relation. The poem’s central homily, the maiden’s long story of the
          parable of the vineyard and the penny, takes as its central problem the issue of relation
          or of equivalence, and specifically the commensurability between the rewards of the
          marketplace and the rewards of heaven: how is it that an infant, the narrator asks, can
          merit the same reward in heaven as those who have lived a long and devout life, or even
          those who have given their lives over to the church in the most directed ways as nuns or
            clerics?<note target="#42" type="footnotelink">42</note> In the parable the maiden tells
          to answer this question, the court — in this case the heavenly court — is ordered by a
          utopic labor system, one that resolves by edict the central tensions about fairness that
          govern market labor and exchange. The parable, a kind of homily or sermon right in the
          middle of the vision, seems surprisingly long and almost digressive, but as an explanation
          of the economics of a heavenly marketplace, it is strategically situated immediately
          before the vision of the New Jerusalem that will put theory into practice. The parable
          offers a textual definition of “paye” or reward.</p>
        <p style="body" n="18">The vision of the New Jerusalem that follows the parable, the most
          elaborately detailed of the poem’s sequence of locations, is itself introduced as a
          problem in relation, voiced in the narrator’s demand to the <hi rend="italic"
          >Pearl</hi>-maiden to know where she lives, and then in his incredulity that she, a
          two-year-old child, could be elevated to the status of a queen in such a place. In
          choosing the New Jerusalem as the climactic moment in which the two-year-old child is
          perceived fully transposed as a full participant in the heavenly court, a bride of the
          Lamb, the poet makes a brilliant strategic move to accommodate, in Kaye’s terms,
          quantities that are incommensurable. As the final location in <hi rend="italic"
          >Pearl</hi>’s sequence of transforming places, the New Jerusalem is a rich and
          multi-layered symbol, understood in medieval theology and allegory to represent the soul,
          heaven, and both ideal city and ideal church. Frequently painted or sculpted on the west
          wall of the church, either inside or out, images of the Lamb and the throne of God and
          images of the Last Judgment marked central points of entrance — and, indeed, the saved
          from the damned. St. Peter’s in Rome, an important pilgrimage site, had on its façade a
          mosaic of the adoration of the Lamb by the twenty-four elders, the same image that is the
          culminating moment in <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>.<note target="#43" type="footnotelink"
            >43</note> In a dramatic final move that ties mystical transport to daily collective
          ritual, the New Jerusalem in <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> also takes the narrative <hi
            rend="italic">into</hi> a church, as if the textual city were itself an invitation over
          a triumphal arch, a theophanic move that is furthered as well by Eucharistic echoes. Some
          readers have suggested that the poem unfolds in imitation of the Mass, and that the pearl
          signifies the host; the round pearl enclosed in gold denotes a round and white Eucharistic
          wafer, displayed in a monstrance<note target="#44" type="footnotelink">44</note> — an
          equivalence that I would argue is just one of many in the poem’s rich metaphoric display.
          The image of the Lamb, both symbol and enactment of the Eucharist, places the narrator,
          and reader as well, before the Eucharist, or more exactly within the performance of the
          Mass. In a final accommodation the New Jerusalem offers a housing not only for the maiden,
          but also for those who participate in the sacraments.</p>
        <p style="body" n="19">The New Jerusalem as depicted in <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> is
          above all a power image, carefully keyed to the tastes and intellectual interests of an
          aristocratic audience in the late Middle Ages. The main textual source is the Book of
          Revelation, but the poet was evidently familiar with visual schema for representing the
          city in Apocalypse cycles, many examples of which survive in deluxe manuscripts.<note
            target="#45" type="footnotelink">45</note> Apocalypse cycles decorated not only the
          triumphal arches of churches and cathedrals, but also royal chapels and chapter houses. An
          elaborate Apocalypse cycle that still decorates the walls of Chapel of the Holy Cross at
          Karlstein Castle in Bohemia offers an example of the close ties between royal interests
          and devotional economics of salvation. Built in 1348–57 at a country residence for Charles
          IV that was also a treasury for the crown jewels, the chapel includes among the scenes
          painted on the walls between the arches the adoration of the Lamb by the elders with
          musical instruments, as in <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>. In this exquisite gothic chapel
          the Apocalypse cycle seems designed to provide a housing not only for the imperial jewels
          but also for imperial souls. The woman clothed with the sun is symbolically equated with
          Anne of Schweidnitz, third wife of Charles IV.<note target="#46" type="footnotelink"
            >46</note> While a chapel in a Bohemian castle may seem remote from the compositional
          context of <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>, shared cultural interests in the late Middle Ages
          and the international movement of artists created a rich cosmopolitan exchange in
          patterns, subjects, and styles. If <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> were produced in the
          circle of Richard II in the 1380s or 1390s, the choice to use the New Jerusalem as the
          poem’s visionary destination could even be imagined as a deliberate one. In 1381 Richard
          married Anne of Bohemia, daughter of Charles IV. Doubtless Anne would have known of her
          father’s chapel at Karlstein and have been familiar with its visual story of the
          Apocalypse. Bennett and Bowers even suggest that <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> may have
          been composed as an elegy for Anne, who died in 1394.<note target="#47"
            type="footnotelink">47</note> If that is so, the New Jerusalem would be an entirely
          fitting housing for her imperial soul. A favorite image for aristocratic patrons, <hi
            rend="italic">Pearl</hi>’s New Jerusalem, one might speculate, was strategically chosen
          to link not only this world with eternity, but also England with Bohemia and a royal
          international lineage.</p>
        <p style="body" n="20">In the culminating vision of the New Jerusalem, the poet overlays
          sharply contrasting ways of knowing and seeing. On the one hand, the narrator moves
          expansively from an enclosed garden to the mystical city; on the other, the dreamer passes
          through the delightfully open meadows of the otherworld to end the vision within a walled
          edifice in many ways evocative of the church. This overlay or juxtaposition in spatial
          resolution gives us the poem’s most skillful act of commensuration, linking the
          unmeasurable with the measurable: we can be both here and there. “Here” and “there” are
          extravagant in latitude. Of the many desires expressed in this poem, a controlling drive
          is a passion for equalizing, the structuring of equivalences according to linguistic,
          musical, and mathematical models that can make it possible for a lost child to be a
          resident of the heavenly kingdom or, for that matter, for ordinary and aristocratic folks
          alike to attain salvation: the parochial moves engaged with the imagery of the New
          Jerusalem suggest that like rewards are available if we will be docile subjects, faithful
          parishioners and observers of the sacraments. Crucial to the narrator’s spiritual
          progress, I would argue, is his understanding of accommodation, the “calculated category
          mistake” that makes it possible for the pearl, or lost child, to be both lost and found.
          On an individual level, <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> describes the difficulties of the
          individual who we might say is “working through” grief with the aid of devotional
          psychology. On the collective level, <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> offers the promise that
          the particular accommodation represented in the vision, the maiden one of 144,000 brides
          of Christ, can be available to all. And if the New Jerusalem suggests a figurative
          movement into clerical space replete with Eucharistic echoes, that transposition is even
          given an explicitly homely dimension in the poem’s final stanza-group, when the narrator
          awakens roughly from the dream to acknowledge the consolation to be found in the daily
          ritual of the Mass, the subjection of the self to the social and ritual order.</p>
        <p style="body" n="21">A question that lingers with <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>, and
          perhaps that accounts for much of its appeal, lies with the body of the narrator: does the
          poem resolve in an aristocratized and utopic vision, or is there a remnant, the narrator
          himself, not totally encapsulated within a formal sacramental or courtly system? The
          narrator skulks the banks of the stream: he cannot cross, and when he tries he awakens,
          and not very happily. Does he become, as he asserts, a docile subject (taking the
          sacrament), or does he remain a single consciousness, separate from the vision of
          metaphoric accumulation that he witnesses?<note target="#48" type="footnotelink">48</note>
          Excluded from paradise, is he the “spot” or blot, the one hundred and first stanza, so to
          speak? Among readers there has been little consensus on this point. Longing and what we
          might call “reality” seem to be across the stream, and perhaps how we read the resolution
          will depend on how compelling we find the poem’s vision of theophany. However communal the
          vision of heaven, that social order, as one reader has put it, is of a fully
          “aristocratized theology.”<note target="#49" type="footnotelink">49</note> Juxtaposed to
          the individualized venture works a public, hierar-chic, and above all courtly
          performance.</p>
        <p style="heading" n="4">Notes on This Edition</p>
        <p style="bodyfirst" n="5"><hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>’s first printer and modern editor
          was Richard Morris, who edited <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> for the Early English Text
          Society in 1864. Before Morris’ edition, <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> had remained in
          manuscript form. The first mention of the poem appears in a catalogue of books belonging
          to Henry Savile of Yorkshire, a collector of manuscripts from the northern monasteries
          (1568–1617). By 1621 the manuscript had been acquired by the antiquarian Sir Robert
          Cotton, where it remained until 1700, when the Cotton collection was given to the British
          nation, and finally to the British Museum in 1753.</p>
        <p style="body" n="22">Early printed editions of <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> tended to the
          view that the copyist, or scribe, had produced a text substantively different from the
          poet’s intent. Israel Gollancz, who edited <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> in 1891 and then
          again in 1921, included in his later edition 124 emendations, or corrections, to the
          manuscript. Many of Gollancz’s emendations were aimed at restoring metrical regularity to
          a poem he understood to be in a form of iambic tetrameter, with four regular stresses to a
            line.<note target="#50" type="footnotelink">50</note> Later editors, however,
          increasingly retained the scribe’s transcription. A tendency to adhere to the scribe’s
          version of the poem was based in part on E. V. Gordon’s influential characterization of
          the poem’s highly problematic meter as a form in effect corrupted by the influence of the
          alliterative long line. Under the influence of writing alliterative verse, the poet wrote
            <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> in a hybrid form that is part metrical verse, part
          alliterative line: “the chief effect of this close relationship is that the line is not
          measured, has not a fixed number of syllables, like the lines of French verse, nor is it
          systematically iambic or anapaestic, as the modern reader tends to make it.”<note
            target="#51" type="footnotelink">51</note> A reluctance to correct potential errors in
          the manuscript also reflects practices in textual editing in general, which have tended
          against emending texts in cases where there is only a single copy. Andrew and Waldron, in
          their important edition of 1979, revised in 1996, have ninety-one emendations, and
          generally follow the lead of Gordon, the poem’s most important modern editor (1953), in
          emending for lexical sense rather than for meter. The most recent edition, William
          Vantuono’s from 1984, aiming to retain manuscript readings “wherever possible,” has only
          twelve emendations.<note target="#52" type="footnotelink">52</note></p>
        <p style="body" n="23">In its use of emendation to restore the regularity of the meter, this
          edition has more in common with Gollancz than with Vantuono. The poet who wrote <hi
            rend="italic">Pearl</hi> had an expert ear for sound, language, and music, and it is
          hard to account for the poem’s many rhythmically clashing stresses and mismetered lines
          unless we attribute them to the poem’s copyists. Recent studies on alliterative meter and
          also on <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> have mounted convincing arguments that the <hi
            rend="italic">Pearl</hi> poet was a careful metrical stylist, and that deviations from
          metrical regularity represent scribal editing rather than authorial intent. Hoyt Duggan
          has recently argued that the poet wrote not in a hybrid and irregularly metrical form, as
          Gordon supposed, but in a regular iambic tetrameter, as described nearly ninety years ago
          in early studies on the poem’s meter and more recently by Marie Borroff.<note target="#53"
            type="footnotelink">53</note> The poem uses alliteration, but in ways markedly different
          from the patternings of unrhymed alliterative poetry.<note target="#54"
            type="footnotelink">54</note> For the purposes of reading, <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>
          should be thought of, as Borroff describes, as “iambic tetrameter varied by an occasional
          anapest” (p. 32), a form that she also compares to Gerard Manly Hopkins’ sprung rhythm.
          There are four stresses to a line, but an irregular number of dips in between stresses.
          Final -<hi rend="italic">e</hi> is not normally sounded, but occasionally it is required
          to avoid clashing stress — required, that is, to provide a dip between two words, often
          monosyllabic, that are stressed, as in line 17, “my herte thrange.” Many of the lines have
          a natural pause, or caesura, in mid-line. In this edition I have added final <hi
            rend="italic">e</hi> to remove clashing stress in the middle of the line, following the
          lead of Gollancz and Duggan.</p>
        <p style="body" n="24">In transcription of the manuscript, I have followed METS guidelines.
          Thorns and edhs are written as <hi rend="italic">th</hi>, and yoghs have been transcribed
          as <hi rend="italic">g</hi>, <hi rend="italic">gh</hi>, <hi rend="italic">y</hi>, <hi
            rend="italic">s</hi>, according to the letter in modern spelling that the sound
          represented by the yogh has come to represent. <hi rend="italic">T</hi> plus yogh is
          written as <hi rend="italic">s</hi>. Manuscript abbreviations have been silently expanded.
          My choices for word division, often ambiguous in the manuscript, are indicated in the
          notes only where the choice of where to divide a word poses a significant interpretive
          problem. The manuscript, like many medieval English texts, is unpunctuated. I have
          punctuated minimally for sense. Lines are only rarely enjambed. In <hi rend="italic"
            >Pearl</hi>, the line is paramount as the unit of thought. In the notes, I have
          indicated manuscript forms as well as emendations adopted among a group of six comparison
          editions.</p>

      </div>
      <div type="footnotes">

        <note type="footnote" n="1"><space rend="indent1"/>Paul Ricoeur, <hi rend="italic">The Rule
            of </hi><hi rend="italic">Metaphor: Multi-disciplinary Studies of the Creation of
            Meaning in </hi><hi rend="italic">Language</hi>, trans. Robert Czerny, with Kathleen
          McLaughlin and John Costello, S. J. (London: Routledge and Kegan Paul, 1978), p. 197;
          Ricoeur takes the idea of the “category mistake” from Gilbert Ryle, <hi rend="italic">The
            Concepts of Mind</hi> (London: Hutchinson, 1949), p. 10.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="2"><space rend="indent1"/>For an important discussion of medieval
          theories of metaphor, see Peter W. Travis, “Chaucer’s Heliotropes and the Poetics of
          Metaphor,” <hi rend="italic">Speculum</hi> 72 (1997), 399–427.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="3"><space rend="indent1"/>For legal judgment, see Silar.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="4"><space rend="indent1"/>I take this term from Tomasch.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="5"><space rend="indent1"/>For Franciscan texts based on 101, see
          Fleming; for discussion of the uses of number in <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>, see Bishop,
            <hi rend="italic">Pearl </hi><hi rend="italic">in Its Setting</hi>, pp. 27–32; Peck, pp.
          44–51, 58–64; Røstvig; and Condren.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="6"><space rend="indent1"/>Fein, pp. 368, 382; Gordon, ed., <hi
            rend="italic">Pearl</hi>, pp. 86–87; David Lawton, “Middle English Alliterative Poetry:
          An Introduction,” in <hi rend="italic">Middle English Alliterative Poetry and Its Literary
            Background: Seven </hi><hi rend="italic">Essays</hi>, ed. David Lawton (Woodbridge,
          Suffolk: D. S. Brewer, 1982), pp. 8–9.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="7"><space rend="indent1"/>Marie Borroff, <hi rend="italic">Pearl: A
            Verse Translation</hi> (New York: W. W. Norton, 1977), p. 35.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="8"><space rend="indent1"/>Darrel Mansell, “Metaphor as Matter,” <hi
            rend="italic">Language and Literature</hi> 17 (1992), 117.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="9"><space rend="indent1"/>Peter Sacks, <hi rend="italic">The
            English Elegy: Studies in the Genre from </hi><hi rend="italic">Spenser to Yeats</hi>
          (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1985), pp. 1–37.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="10"><space rend="indent1"/>Stanbury, “The Body and the City in <hi
            rend="italic">Pearl</hi>”; for the gendering of the poem’s embodied language, see
          Cox.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="11"><space rend="indent1"/>Muscatine, pp. 37, 40; see also Putter,
          who speaks of the poet’s “techniques of defamiliarization” (p. 156).</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="12"><space rend="indent1"/>Angus McIntosh, “A New Approach to
          Middle English Dialectology,” <hi rend="italic">English Studies</hi> 44 (1963), 1–11; H.
          N. Duggan, “Meter, Stanza, Vocabulary, Dialect,” in Brewer and Gibson, pp. 240–42.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="13"><space rend="indent1"/>For a discussion of this question and of
          regional versus urban production in Ricardian poetry, see Turville-Petre, pp.
          276–94.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="14"><space rend="indent1"/>Duggan, “Meter,” pp. 238–39, cites
          Norman Hinton, “The Language of the <hi rend="italic">Gawain</hi>-Poems,” <hi
            rend="italic">Arthurian Interpretations</hi> 2 (1987), 83–94, and an unpublished paper
          by Hinton.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="15"><space rend="indent1"/>W. G. Cooke, “<hi rend="italic">Sir
            Gawain and the Green Knight</hi>: A Restored Dating,” <hi rend="italic">Medium </hi><hi
            rend="italic">Aevum</hi> 58 (1989), 34–48.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="16"><space rend="indent1"/>Fein, p. 393.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="17"><space rend="indent1"/>C. E. Wright, <hi rend="italic">English
            Vernacular Hands from the Twelfth to the </hi><hi rend="italic">Fifteenth Centuries</hi>
          (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1960), p. 15.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="18"><space rend="indent1"/>For a review of the discussion, see
          Andrew, “Theories of Authorship,” in Brewer and Gibson, pp. 26–28. For a recent argument
          including <hi rend="italic">St. Erkenwald</hi>, see Borroff, “Narrative Artistry.”</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="19"><space rend="indent1"/>A. S. G. Edwards, “The Manuscript:
          British Library MS Cotton Nero A.x,” in Brewer and Gibson, pp. 197, 210. For a
          reconsideration of the illustrations and argument that they were composed with attention
          to the numerological and thematic issues of the poems, see Reichardt.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="20"><space rend="indent1"/>For a study of the thematic similarities
          among the four poems, see Spearing, <hi rend="italic">The Gawain-Poet</hi>.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="21"><space rend="indent1"/>Oscar Cargill and Margaret Schlauch,
          “The Pearl and Its Jeweler,” <hi rend="italic">PMLA</hi> 43 (1928), 105–23.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="22"><space rend="indent1"/>For essays advancing the Mascy
          hypothesis, see Ormerod Greenwood, trans., <hi rend="italic">Sir Gawain and the </hi><hi
            rend="italic">Green Knight</hi> (London: Lion and Unicorn Press, 1956), pp. 6–12;
          Barbara Nolan and David Farley-Hills, “The Authorship of <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>: Two
          Notes,” <hi rend="italic">Review of English Studies</hi> n.s. 22 (1971), 295–302; William
          Vantuono, “A Name in the Cotton MS. Nero A.x Article 3,” <hi rend="italic">Medieval
            Studies</hi> 34 (1975), 537–42, and “John de Mascy ”; Katherine Adam, <hi rend="italic"
            >The Anomalous Stanza of Pearl: </hi><hi rend="italic">Does it Disclose a Six-Hundred
            Year Old Secret?</hi> (Fayetteville: Monograph Publishers, 1976); Eric Kooper, “The Case
          of the Encoded Author: John Massey in <hi rend="italic">Sir Gawain and the Green
            Knight</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Neuphilologische Mitteilungen</hi> 83 (1982), 158–68.
          For counter arguments see Thorlac Turville-Petre and Edward Wilson, “Hoccleve, ‘Maister
          Massy’, and the <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>-Poet: Two Notes,” <hi rend="italic">Review of
            English Studies</hi> n.s. 26 (1975), 129–43; Clifford Peterson and Edward Wilson,
          “Hoccleve, the Old Hall Manuscript, Cotton Nero A.x and the <hi rend="italic"
          >Pearl</hi>-Poet,” <hi rend="italic">Review of English Studies</hi> n.s. 28 (1977), 49–56.
          These arguments are summarized in detail by Andrew, in Brewer and Gibson, pp. 28–31; see
          also William Vantuono, ed., <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"> Pearl Poems</hi>,
          pp. xxii–xxiv. </note>
        <note type="footnote" n="23"><space rend="indent1"/>James Wimsatt, <hi rend="italic">The
            Marguerite</hi><hi rend="italic"> Poetry of Guillaume de Machaut</hi> (Chapel Hill:
          University of North Carolina Press, 1970), pp. 40–41; see also Travis, “Chaucer’s
          Heliotropes,” pp. 404–05.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="24"><space rend="indent1"/>For symbolism of pearls, see Donkin, pp.
          250–75; and for studies with application to <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>, see Bishop, <hi
            rend="italic">Pearl in Its Setting</hi>, pp. 51–98; Kean, pp. 143–47; Bogdanos; and the
          brief but cogent discussion in Gordon, ed., pp. xxvii–xxix. For readings of the poem as
          developmental spiritual allegory, see Blenkner; Wimsatt, pp. 122–33; Hamilton; Finlayson;
          and Clopper.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="25"><space rend="indent1"/>Gollancz, in his 1921 edition, provides
          an imaginary biography for the poet in which a formative episode is his daughter’s death,
          pp. xl–xlvi. A more recent autobiographical narrative has been constructed by Bowers, “The
          Politics of <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>,” pp. 432–41.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="26"><space rend="indent1"/>Gollancz, pp. 258–85, appends an edition
          and translation of <hi rend="italic">Olympia</hi> to his edition.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="27"><space rend="indent1"/>See note 21.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="28"><space rend="indent1"/>Michael J. Bennett, “The Historical
          Background,” in Brewer and Gibson, p. 84; the argument is detailed at length in John
          Bowers, <hi rend="italic">The Politics of Pearl: Court Poetry</hi>.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="29"><space rend="indent1"/>Bishop, <hi rend="italic">Pearl in Its
            Setting</hi>, pp. 113–21; Staley, “<hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> and the Contingencies of
          Love and Piety.”</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="30"><space rend="indent1"/>See Riddy, in Brewer and Gibson; Bowers,
            “<hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> in Its Royal Setting,” p. 139; and especially Barr.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="31"><space rend="indent1"/>See David Aers, “Christianity for
          Courtly Subjects,” in Brewer and Gibson, p. 94.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="32"><space rend="indent1"/>Bennett, “The Court of Richard II,” pp.
          11–16; and Bennett, “The Historical Background,” p. 78.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="33"><space rend="indent1"/>Bennett, “The Historical Background,” p.
          81.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="34"><space rend="indent1"/>Bowers, “<hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> in
          Its Royal Setting,” pp. 419–41.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="35"><space rend="indent1"/>Gervase Mathew, <hi rend="italic">The
            Court of Richard II</hi> (London: Murray, 1968), pp. 38–39.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="36"><space rend="indent1"/>Bowers, “<hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> in
          Its Royal Setting,” pp. 145–51.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="37"><space rend="indent1"/>Bennett, “The Court of Richard II,” pp.
          14–16; and Bowers, “<hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> in Its Royal Setting,” pp. 151–55.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="38"><space rend="indent1"/>J. P. Oakden, <hi rend="italic"
            >Alliterative Poetry in Middle English</hi> (Manchester: Manchester University Press,
          1930), pp. 261–63; cited in Fein, p. 369n.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="39"><space rend="indent1"/>Joel Kaye, <hi rend="italic">Economy and
            Nature in the Fourteenth </hi><hi rend="italic">Century: Money, Market Exchange, and the
            Emergence of Scientific Thought</hi> (New York: Cambridge University Press, 1998), pp.
          3, 219.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="40"><space rend="indent1"/>James Wimsatt, Chaucer and his French
          Contemporaries: Natural Music in the Fourteenth Century (Toronto: University of Toronto
          Press, 1993), p. 96.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="41"><space rend="indent1"/>Travis, “Chaucer’s Heliotropes,” pp.
          403–05.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="42"><space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>’s theology
          of reward has been recently addressed by Watson, “The <hi rend="italic">Gawain</hi>-Poet
          as a Vernacular Theologian,” in Brewer and Gibson, pp. 293–313. The relationship between
          the parable of the vineyard and concerns with labor and economics in late
          fourteenth-century England is addressed by Bowers, “The Politics of <hi rend="italic"
            >Pearl</hi>,” pp. 419–41; and by Watkins.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="43"><space rend="indent1"/>See Jonathan Alexander, with Michael
          Michael and Martin Kauffmann, “The Last Things: Representing the Unrepresentable,” in <hi
            rend="italic">The Apocalypse and the Shape of Things to </hi><hi rend="italic"
          >Come</hi>, ed. Frances Carey (London: British Museum Press, 1999), pp. 49, 44.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="44"><space rend="indent1"/>See Phillips; Marti, pp. 44, 84–88; and
          Gatta.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="45"><space rend="indent1"/>See Whitaker; Field; Nolan, pp. 54–83;
          and Stanbury, <hi rend="italic">Seeing the Gawain-Poet</hi>, pp. 21–35.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="46"><space rend="indent1"/>Vlasta Dvoraková, J. Krása, A.
          Merhautová, and K. Stejskal, <hi rend="italic">Gothic Mural Painting in</hi><hi
            rend="italic"> Bohemia and Moravia 1300–1378</hi>, trans. R. Finlayson-Samsour and I.
          Urwin (London: Oxford University Press, 1964), p. 97; Alfred Thomas, <hi rend="italic"
            >Anne’s Bohemia: Czech Literature and Society 1310–1420</hi> (Minneapolis: University of
          Minnesota Press, 1998), p. 101.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="47"><space rend="indent1"/>Thomas, p. 19, also proposes Anne as a
          candidate.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="48"><space rend="indent1"/>For the text’s representation of
          individual self-consciousness, see Aers; and Watkins.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="49"><space rend="indent1"/>Watson, in Brewer and Gibson, p.
          312.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="50"><space rend="indent1"/>Gollancz, pp. xxiii–ivn. Gollancz’s
          understanding of the poem as iambic tetrameter was based on an essay by C. S. Northup, “A
          Study of the Metrical Structure of the Middle English Poem <hi rend="italic">The
            Pearl</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">PMLA</hi> 12 (1897), 326–40.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="51"><space rend="indent1"/>Gordon, p. 89.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="52"><space rend="indent1"/>Vantuono, <hi rend="italic">The Pearl
            Poems</hi>, pp. liv–lv.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="53"><space rend="indent1"/>Duggan, “Libertine Scribes,” pp. 219–37;
          and Duggan, “Meter, Stanza, Vocabulary, Dialect,” in Brewer and Gibson, pp. 221–42. <hi
            rend="italic">Pearl</hi> was first characterized as iambic tetrameter by Northrup; for a
          succinct description of the form in <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> see Borroff, <hi
            rend="italic">Pearl</hi>, pp. 32–35.</note>
        <note type="footnote" n="54"><space rend="indent1"/>Duggan’s argument that the poet wrote a
          metrically regular line that the scribe, or scribes, transformed is based in part on
          recent studies defining the metrical characteristics of the alliterative long line; see
          Duggan, “Final –E and the Rhythmic Structure of the B-Verse in Middle English Alliterative
          Poetry,” <hi rend="italic">Modern Philology</hi> 86 (1988), 119–45; Marie Borroff, <hi
            rend="italic">Sir</hi><hi rend="italic"> Gawain and the Green Knight: A Stylistic and
            Metrical Study</hi> (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1962); and Thorlac
          Turville-Petre, <hi rend="italic">The Alliterative Revival</hi> (Cambridge: D. S. Brewer,
          1977). In <hi rend="italic">Sir</hi><hi rend="italic"> Gawain and the Green Knight</hi>,
            <hi rend="italic">Cleanness</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Patience</hi>, the three
          alliterative poems of the manuscript, the scribe consistently makes lines unmetrical by
          the uses of dissyllabic forms, writing <hi rend="italic">other</hi> for <hi rend="italic"
            >or</hi>. In copying <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>, the scribe makes similar changes,
          using dissyllabic forms to transform metrically regular lines to unmetrical ones; Duggan,
          “Libertine Scribes,” pp. 224–25.</note>


      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
