<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" version="3.3.0"
  xml:id="Stanbury-Pearl-Export-05-Enotes-tei">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Explanatory Notes</title>
        <author>Stanbury, Sarah</author>
        <sponsor>The University of Rochester</sponsor>
        <sponsor>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</sponsor>
        <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
        <funder>The University of Rochester</funder>
        <funder>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Amster, Mara I.</persName>
          <resp>Prepared edition for publication</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Conrath, Ryan</persName>
          <resp>Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp>Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Delcourt, Steffi</persName>
          <resp from="2025-04" to="2025-05">Audited documents prior to print/export</resp>
          <resp from="2025-04" to="2025-04">Collected metadata</resp>
          <resp from="2025-01" to="2025-02">Copyedited and proofread</resp>
          <resp from="2025-04" to="2025-05">Encoded TEI</resp>
          <resp from="2025-04" to="2025-04">Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp>
          <resp from="2025-01" to="2025-04">Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp from="2025-01" to="2025-02">Entered corrections for print edition</resp>
          <resp from="2025-01" to="2025-02">Formatted for print edition</resp>
          <resp from="2025-01" to="2025-04">Formatted for XML export</resp>
          <resp from="2025-05" to="2025-05">Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Johnson-Olin, Martha M.</persName>
          <resp>Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp>Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Kephart, Daniel</persName>
          <resp from="2024-02" to="2024-02">Collected metadata</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Lupack, Alan</persName>
          <resp>Copyedited and proofread</resp>
          <resp>Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp>
          <resp>Reviewed and suggested explanatory notes</resp>
          <resp>Reviewed edition for consistency and audience</resp>
          <resp>Reviewed edition for content and scholarship</resp>
          <resp>Wrote reader report</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>McShane, Kara L.</persName>
          <resp>Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp>Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Peck, Russell A.</persName>
          <resp>Copyedited and proofread</resp>
          <resp>Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp>
          <resp>Reviewed and suggested explanatory notes</resp>
          <resp>Reviewed edition for consistency and audience</resp>
          <resp>Reviewed edition for content and scholarship</resp>
          <resp>Wrote reader report</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Roth, Aaron</persName>
          <resp>Entered corrections for digital edition</resp>
          <resp>Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Symons, Dana M.</persName>
          <resp>Prepared edition for publication</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Encoded in TEI in 2025.</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Rossell Hope Robbins Library, University of Rochester</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>https://www.library.rochester.edu/spaces/robbins</addrLine>
        </address>
        <publisher>The Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>https://www.sas.rochester.edu/eng/</addrLine>
        </address>
        <publisher>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>https://teams-medieval.org/about/</addrLine>
        </address>
        <distributor>The Rossell Hope Robbins Library, University of Rochester</distributor>
        <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>https://www.library.rochester.edu/spaces/robbins</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Downloading shall be restricted to one copy for private use.</p>
        </availability>
        <date/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="s">The Middle English Text Series</title>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Mara I. Amster</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Rita Copeland</persName>
          <orgName>University of Pennsylvania</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Thomas G. Hahn</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Lisa J. Kiser</persName>
          <orgName>Ohio State University</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Alan Lupack</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Associate Editor, Editorial Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Russell A. Peck</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>General Editor, Editorial Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Thomas H. Seiler</persName>
          <orgName>Western Michigan University</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>R. A. Shoaf</persName>
          <orgName>University of Florida</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>John William Sutton</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Dana M. Symons</persName>
          <orgName>University of Rochester</orgName>
          <resp>Assistant Editor, Editorial Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Bonnie Wheeler</persName>
          <orgName>Southern Methodist University</orgName>
          <resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>Unknown</author>
            <editor>Stanbury, Sarah</editor>
            <title>Pearl</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Medieval Institute Publications</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Kalamazoo, MI</pubPlace>
              <date>2001</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Middle English Texts Series offers a diverse and representative array of literary
          texts that medieval readers in the present-day British Isles would have encountered
          between the twelfth and sixteenth centuries. It is committed to making available both
          affordable print and open access editions to scholars, teachers, and students of the
          Western Middle Ages. In its digital publications, the series prioritizes a user-friendly
          interface and viewing options, multiple downloadable formats, enhanced searchability and
          filtering, and accessibility to the widest possible range of users.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>METS takes as its mission the creation of affordable editions that would pass scrutiny
          from the most demanding expert, yet would prove comprehensible, and even enticing, to
          someone who had never read Middle English before. This agenda dictates that METS
          publications offer not a critical edition reflecting all surviving manuscripts, and
          certainly not a diplomatic edition, but a best-text edition, informed by the notes and
          apparatus of earlier editions (where these exist), and by substantive variants from other
          manuscript witnesses. Transcriptions of Middle English texts are lightly modernized to
          ensure a smooth reading experience, while non-English texts preserve both the original
          language and a modern English translation in facing-page format. Each edition offers
          expert assistance with language and lexicon, providing glosses alongside the text(s),
          textual and explanatory notes, elucidation of unfamiliar contexts and traditions, and
          thematic and interpretive possibilities. All editions feature general introductions that
          set the edited text within its own time, place, and traditions, and link it to ancestor,
          congener, and successor materials. All publications contain comprehensive, current
          bibliographies of pertinent scholarship and criticism. House style is adapted from the <hi
            rend="italic">Chicago Manual of Style</hi>.</p>
        <correction>
          <p>This text may include corrections made after the original edition went to press in
            order to correct errors and improve glosses. For a full list of editorial and
            typographical corrections made to this edition, please view its correction log on
            Github:
            https://github.com/mets-editions/stanbury-pearl/blob/main/stanbury-pearl-export-corrections-log.docx</p>
        </correction>
      </editorialDecl>
      <schemaRef url="https://metseditions.org/schema/mets-editions.xsd"/>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English, Modern (1500-present)</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>First edition published in 2001</change>
      <change>Encoded in HTML</change>
      <change>Entered editorial corrections in 2025</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
      <anchor xml:id="Stanbury-Pearl-Export-05-Enotes"/>
      <div type="text">
        <note type="enote" n="1">1<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Perle</hi>. The pearl is
          the text’s central object and symbol. Pearls were luxury items, widely used to decorate
          expensive clothing and precious objects: the <hi rend="italic">Breviaire de
            Belleville</hi> that Richard II received in 1396 as a gift from Philip the Bold had a
          cover studded with pearls, as described by Jeanne Krochalis, “The Books and Reading of
          Henry V and His Circle,” <hi rend="italic">Chaucer Review</hi> 23 (1988), 59–60. The
          immense popularity of pearls as decorative items in the fourteenth century is attested by
          the inventory of Alice Perrers, mistress of Edward III, when her goods were seized in
          1379, listing 21,800 pearls and 30 ounces of seed pearls (Frederick Devon, <hi
            rend="italic">Issues of the Exchequer; Being a Collection of</hi><hi rend="italic">
            Payments Made out of His Majesty’s Revenue, from King</hi><hi rend="italic"> Henry III
            to King Henry VI Inclusive. With an Appendix</hi><hi rend="italic">. Extracted and
            Translated from the Original Rolls of the Ancient</hi><hi rend="italic"> Pell Office,
            Now Remaining in the Custody of the Right</hi><hi rend="italic"> Honourable Sir John
            Newport, Bart. Comptroller-General of His Majesty</hi><hi rend="italic">’s
            Exchequer</hi>. Vol. 2 [London: J. Murray, 1837], pp. 209–10; cited in Donkin, p. 268).
          The most valuable pearls were imported from the far east (“Oute of Oryent,” line 3) via
          the Mediterranean. The analogy between the pearl of price and the kingdom of heaven,
          explicated in lines 732–35, derives from the parable in Matthew 13:45–46, and was a
          popular allegorical theme for medieval theologians. Pearls were also conventionally
          equated with the pure soul and virginity, as described in the etymology opening the legend
          of St. Margaret in the immensely popular <hi rend="italic">Golden Legend</hi> by Jacobus
          de Voragine, and with the Virgin Mary, the star of the sea (<hi rend="italic">stella
            maris</hi>). For gems in late fourteenth-century court culture, see Riddy, in Brewer and
          Gibson; Barr; and Bowers, “<hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> in Its Royal Setting”; and for
          pearls, see Donkin, “Pearls in the Medieval World,” pp. 250–75; Lightbown, pp. 30–31; and
          R. Allen Shoaf’s edition of Usk’s <hi rend="italic">The Testament of Love</hi> (Kalamazoo,
          MI: Medieval Institute Publications, 1998), pp. 8–10, with frontispiece reproductions of
          the Virgin Mary and babe, the pearl as both star of the sea, and a pearl oyster in the
          sea, from MS Bodley 602, fol. 34. In <hi rend="italic">The </hi><hi rend="italic"
            >Apocryphal New Testament</hi>, ed. M. R. James (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1953), pp.
          209–16, Mary at the moment of her Assumption is compared to a pearl: “Then the Saviour
          spoke [to Mary], saying: ‘Come, thou most precious pearl, enter into the treasury
          (receptacle) of eternal life.’”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="2"><space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">paye</hi>. Used as a verb
            <hi rend="italic">paye</hi> means both “to please” and “to pay.” <hi rend="italic"
            >Paye</hi>, with its suggestions of both worldly commerce and also spiritual rewards, is
          the link-word of the final stanza group and the last word of the poem.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="3">2<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">To clanly clos</hi>.
          Unpunctuated, as is the whole manuscript, this line has been variously interpreted: “too
          chastely set in gold” (G), “for a splendid setting” (V), or “to set radiantly in gold so
          clear,” as other editors, myself included, have read the line. <hi rend="italic"
            >Clanly</hi> is also used in Middle English in the sense of “cleanly,”
          “chastely.”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="4">3<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Oute of Oryent</hi>.
          I.e., where the best pearls come from. See note to line 1.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="5">4<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Ne . . . never</hi>.
          Double negatives are equivalent to single negatives. “I never found her precious peer
          (equal in value).”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="6">5<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">reken</hi>. As an
          attribute of person, <hi rend="italic">reken</hi> can mean “capable” or
          “righteous.”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="7"><space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">araye</hi>. Pertains to
          forms of display or ordering and can range in meaning from the concrete to the
          abstract.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="8">6<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">sydes</hi>. The term
          appears elsewhere in the poem to denote a feature of landscape, as in hill side (line 73)
          or the side of a river (line 975), but in Middle English <hi rend="italic">syde</hi> is
          often anatomical and a standard of courtly rhetoric for denoting a woman’s figure or
          clothing; see <hi rend="italic">sydes</hi> as features of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Pearl</hi>-maiden’s garment, lines 198 and 218. The use of the term in the opening stanza
          foreshadows the metonomy that will link pearl with maiden. For discussions of gender and
          embodiment in <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>, see Bullon-Fernandez; Cox; and Stanbury,
          “Feminist Masterplots” and “The Body and the City.”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="9">9<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">erbere</hi>. The <hi
            rend="italic">MED</hi> gives as its first definition for <hi rend="italic">herber</hi> a
          “pleasure garden,” which is borne out here by the description of spice plants and flowers.
          See Luttrell.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="10">10<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">hit</hi>. Gor explains
          that conventions in Middle English for indicating gender were, to an extent,
          case-dependent. Whereas “poetic license” might allow interchange between masculine and
          feminine pronouns when a word is used as a direct object or object of a preposition, in
          subject position a pronoun signals a clear mark of gender C or its absence. Hence the uses
          of the feminine “hyr” as direct agent in lines 4, 6, 8, and 9, but the neuter <hi
            rend="italic">hit</hi> as subject of the verb in line 10. As both Gor and AW note, the
          uses of “hyr” hint at the pearl’s feminine apotheosis, even as the neuter <hi
            rend="italic">hit</hi> returns us to the gemstone.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="11"><space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">yot</hi>. I follow H and
          AW in reading <hi rend="italic">yot</hi> as derived from <hi rend="italic">yette</hi>, “to
          pour, tumble”; see <hi rend="italic">OED</hi>
          <hi rend="italic">yet</hi>. Other editors have read the unusual <hi rend="italic">yot</hi>
          as a variant spelling of <hi rend="italic">yode</hi>, past tense of the verb <hi
            rend="italic">gon</hi>, “to go.” “Tumble,” coupled with the subsequent “sprange” in line
          13, suggests the pearl’s vivacity and even agency.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="12">11<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">luf-daungere</hi>.
          Apparently a unique compound in Middle English, <hi rend="italic">luf-daungere</hi> is a
          term from courtly love and evokes desire for the unattainable as well as feudal service to
          the lady, from OF <hi rend="italic">daungere</hi>, “feudal power,” as AW note. Compare
          Chaucer’s The Wife of Bath’s Prologue, where Alisoun says her fifth husband “was of his
          love daungerous to me” (<hi rend="italic">CT</hi> III[D]514). In <hi rend="italic">Le
            Roman de la Rose</hi> Dangiers signifies the lady’s refusal; see lines 2831–32.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="13">12<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">pryvy</hi>. From OF <hi
            rend="italic">privé</hi>, it has the sense of personal, intimate, or one’s own.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="14"><space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">spot</hi>. The link-word
          of the first stanza group, <hi rend="italic">spot</hi> conveys the double senses of
          blemish and place that remain in contemporary usage. For link-words see Macrae-Gibson and
          Tomasch.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="15">17<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">That</hi>. I.e.,
          pondering and wishing, which only cause pain.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="16">19<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">swete a sange</hi>. The
          orchestration of sound into song is a central component of the narrator’s vision of the
          landscape and of the New Jerusalem, as in lines 91–94, 877–88, and 1123–28. As Gor notes,
          the song is also the lyric and text of <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> itself.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="17">23<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">juele</hi>. G emends to
            <hi rend="italic">mele</hi>, i.e., a “merry theme,” yoking song and pearl. Subsequent
          editors have not followed suit. Riddy, in Brewer and Gibson, p. 147, notes that Middle
          English <hi rend="italic">juele</hi> means not only a gemstone but also a precious art
          object. See also Barr.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="18">28<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">schyne</hi>. MS: <hi
            rend="italic">schyneȝ</hi>. I follow AW who emend to <hi rend="italic">schyne</hi> to
          correct for grammatical agreement. <hi rend="italic">Schyne</hi> and “sprede” (line 25)
          both depend on “mot nedes” (line 25) a reading consistent with the stanza’s picture of
          natural conditionality: that spot must be overgrown with spice plants; flowers must shine.
          This stanza imagines the cycle of decay and regeneration in the “erber”; the fourth stanza
          will then move to direct experience when the narrator recounts his entrance into the
          garden. Note the uses of the conditional and the convoluted negatives that mark this
          stanza’s exposition of regeneration.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="19">29<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">fede</hi>. Most editors
          read as “faded” from OF <hi rend="italic">fade</hi>, with the vowel <hi rend="italic"
            >a</hi> modified to <hi rend="italic">e</hi> by poet or scribe for rhyme. My reading
          accords with G, who translates as “rotted” or “decayed” from the ON <hi rend="italic"
            >feyja</hi>, a reading supported by the <hi rend="italic">MED</hi> as well as the
          stanza’s display of rot and regeneration as a causal cycle.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="20">31–32<space rend="indent1"/>This proverbial phrase is based on I
          Corinthians 15:34–38 and John 12:24, as Gor notes.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="21">39<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">hygh seysoun</hi>. In
          medieval texts dates are customarily identified by the event celebrated in the religious
          calendar, rather than by the lunar calendar as in modern practice. Here the high season
          may refer to the Feast of the Assumption of the Virgin on August 15; the Feast of the
          Transfiguration of Christ on August 8; or Lammastide, on August 1, a harvest festival in
          which bread made from the first harvested grain was offered in the churches; see Christina
          Hole, <hi rend="italic">English Traditional </hi><hi rend="italic">Customs</hi> (London:
          Batsford, 1975), p. 89. The following line defining <hi rend="italic">hygh seysoun</hi>
          through the actions of the harvest supports Lammastide, as G first argued.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="22">44<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">powdered</hi>. To
          powder or to scatter also suggests decorative illustration, often in heraldry as in <hi
            rend="italic">OED</hi>
          <hi rend="italic">powder</hi>, v.1, sense 4, “to ornament with spots or small devices
          scattered over the surface,” as V notes. Terms describing the landscape in the language of
          manuscript illumination also appear in lines 77–78, 106.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="23">43–44<space rend="indent1"/>All the flowers named are highly
          aromatic and had uses as spices in the Middle Ages, adding to the picture of the “erber”
          as a pleasure garden. See Stern; as G first noted, the list of plants is reminiscent of
          the spice garden in <hi rend="italic">Le Roman de la Rose</hi>; compare Chaucer’s
          translation, lines 1367–72. In the <hi rend="italic">Romaunt</hi>, the spices are
          after-dinner condiments: “And many a spice delitable / To eten whan men rise fro table”
          (lines 1371–72).</note>
        <note type="enote" n="24">45<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">hit</hi>. I.e., the
          “spot” (line 37), “erber” (line 38), and “huyle” (line 41) where the pearl was
          lost.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="25">47<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">wot and wene</hi>. A
          verse tag and alliterative formula.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="26">59<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">slepyng-slaghte</hi>.
            <hi rend="italic">Slaghte</hi> is derived from OE <hi rend="italic">slæht</hi>, meaning
          slaughter or a violent stroke, and normally means a sudden blow in Middle English; see AW
          and Gor.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="27">61<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">in space</hi>. AW, Gor,
          and H read <hi rend="italic">in space</hi> as “in a space of time.” I accord with other
          editors in favoring reading <hi rend="italic">space</hi> as location, though both meanings
          may well apply.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="28">62<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">sweven</hi>. Dreams are
          conventional points of departure for many philosophical or political verse narratives
          (dream visions) in the Middle Ages. Although truth of dreams was much debated, majority
          opinion appears to have taken seriously their prophetic and revelatory potential. See
          Lynch, pp. 1–46, but also pp. 163, 193; and Nolan, pp. 156–204. Chaucer gives a vivid
          replay of the debate in The Nun’s Priest’s Tale.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="29">71<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">webbes</hi>. Throughout
          the text the poet frequently makes analogies between natural forms and works of art or
          craft (here textiles); see for instance lines 76, 77, 114, and note to line 44.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="30">91<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">sytole-stryng</hi>. The
          citole was a plucked instrument similar to the lute, and a precursor to the
          cittern.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="31"><space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">gyternere</hi>. A gittern
          was a guitar-like instrument, usually with four strings.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="32">95<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">gle</hi>. Also means
          “mirth,” “entertainment.”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="33">105<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">reveres</hi>. Although
            <hi rend="italic">reveres</hi> usually means “rivers” in alliterative poetry, the word
          can also mean “meadows along a streambank,” a sense more in keeping with the logic of the
          dreamer’s movement toward a body of water, as Gor notes. H and V gloss as “rivers.”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="34">113<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">stepe</hi>. As Gor
          notes, <hi rend="italic">stepe</hi> is often used in Middle English to refer to eyes
          “staring” or “glaring,” though it is also used to convey the sense of “brilliant.”
          “Staring” evokes the action of visual rays that is also suggested in “stremande” (line
          115) and “[s]taren” (line 116). The passage as a whole animates place with extromissive
          powers of vision, even as the people sleep. For vision in medieval aesthetics, see Michael
          Camille, <hi rend="italic">Gothic Art: Visions and Revelations in the Medieval</hi><hi
            rend="italic"> World</hi> (London: Weidenfeld and Nicolson, 1996), pp.16–25; Norman
          Klassen, <hi rend="italic">Chaucer on Love, Knowledge and Sight</hi> (Cambridge: D. S.
          Brewer, 1995), pp. 53–74; and Stanbury, <hi rend="italic">Seeing the Gawain</hi><hi
            rend="italic">-Poet</hi>, pp. 12–41.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="35">115<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">strothe-men</hi>. The
          term is uncertain. Gor argues that <hi rend="italic">stroth</hi> had the meaning of
          “marshy land (overgrown with brushwood),” and <hi rend="italic">strothe-men</hi> likely
          means “men of this world.” Ralph W. V. Elliott, “Some Northern Landscape Features in <hi
            rend="italic">Sir Gawain and the</hi><hi rend="italic"> Green Knight</hi>,” in <hi
            rend="italic">Iceland and the Mediaeval World: Studies</hi><hi rend="italic"> in Honour
            of Ian Maxwell</hi>, ed. Gabriel Turville-Petre and John S. Martin (Melbourne:
          Organising Committee, 1974), pp. 132–43, notes that in Old Icelandic <hi rend="italic"
            >storth</hi> carries the sense of a young wood or plantation and hence proposes “country
          folk, woodlanders.” Evidently the poet is juxtaposing extremes from the stars on high to
          swamp dwellers at the bottom through which distance the wondrous light streams.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="36">117<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">pyght</hi>. <hi
            rend="italic">Pyght</hi> is frequently used in the poem to describe adornment with
          pearls or gems; see lines 192, 205, 217, 229, 240, and 241.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="37">129<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">fraynes</hi>. A, Gor,
          and H translate <hi rend="italic">fraynes</hi> as “makes trial” or “puts (men) to the
          test.” I accord with G and V in translating as “wishes,” a gloss the <hi rend="italic"
            >MED</hi> supports.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="38">131<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">her </hi><hi
            rend="italic">wylle</hi>. AW emend to <hi rend="italic">his</hi>, believing <hi
            rend="italic">her</hi> to be a scribal error for <hi rend="italic">his</hi>, and read
          the lines, “the man to whom she sends his desire seeks to have more and more (of it).” As
          I read the lines, <hi rend="italic">her wylle</hi> conveys the sense of fortune as the
          catalyst of the will, which in turn incites desire, “ay more and more” (line 132).</note>
        <note type="enote" n="39">132<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Hyttes</hi>. AW gloss
          as “seek, wish”; A, G, and Gor gloss as “comes, chances, attains as a result”; H reads as
          “is likely.” “Casts” in the sense of “thrusts,” might also be implied. The <hi
            rend="italic">more</hi> that fortune sends is further specified in the next
          stanza.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="40">139–40<space rend="indent1"/>Most editors generally accord with
          Gor: “I thought the stream was a division made by pools, separating the delights” — i.e.,
          the delights on both sides of the water. G emends line 140 to <hi rend="italic">Bytwene
            meres by Myrthe made</hi>. D. C. Fowler, “On the Meaning of <hi rend="italic"
          >Pearl</hi>, 139–40,” <hi rend="italic">MLQ</hi> 21 (1960), 27–29, offers the suggestion,
          “I thought that the water was a deception / Made by meres among the delights.”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="41">161<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">faunt</hi>. The <hi
            rend="italic">MED</hi> gives “young child” and “infant” for <hi rend="italic">faunt</hi>
          (from OF <hi rend="italic">enfaunt</hi>), though H translates as “youthful being.”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="42">165<space rend="indent1"/>The comparison is to sheets of gold
          leaf, consistent with a pattern of analogy between the sights of the dreamer’s vision and
          manuscript illumination.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="43">172<space rend="indent1"/>AW read: “as had been but little wont to
          do so before,” as do A and G. I accord with V and H in reading <hi rend="italic"
            >lyttel</hi> as a duration of time: “as a short while ago was wont thereto” (H). Gor
          notes both readings are possible.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="44">184<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">hawk in halle</hi>. A
          courtly hunting image, consistent with his fears of her escape (“eschaped”) in line
          187.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="45">197<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">beau biys</hi>. MS
          shows five minims, or vertical strokes, between <hi rend="italic">a</hi> and <hi
            rend="italic">y</hi>. A, AW, and Gor read as <hi rend="italic">beau biys</hi>,
          “beautiful white linen garment,” after Revelation 19:8, where the bride of the lamb is
          arrayed in splendid “byssinum.” As Riddy, in Brewer and Gibson, p. 144, notes, citations
          in the <hi rend="italic">MED</hi> make it clear that biys is a luxury cloth. G, H, and V
          read as <hi rend="italic">beaumys</hi>, with <hi rend="italic">be</hi> as “around” and <hi
            rend="italic">mys</hi> derived from Latin <hi rend="italic">amice</hi>, “cape” or
          “surcoat”: hence “mantle or surcoat.”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="46">199<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">at my </hi><hi
            rend="italic">devyse</hi>. Editors have read <hi rend="italic">at my devyse</hi> as “in
          my opinion,” a common expression in Middle English. It is possible the phrase may also
          refer to a heraldic emblem or coat of arms, i.e., “after my device,” and hence the
          daughter’s dress as a heraldic gown. <hi rend="italic">OED</hi> “device,” sense 9, gives
          “an emblematic figure or design . . . heraldic bearing.” In line 856 the <hi rend="italic"
            >Pearl</hi>-maiden speaks of her pearls as a heraldic crest. Froissart mentions the
          dresses of ladies attending the jousts in Smithfield as decorated with the livery of
          Richard II. In <hi rend="italic">Confessio Amantis</hi>, Gower describes a group of ladies
          dressed after the new fashion introduced by Anne of Bohemia, “the new guise of Beme,” as
          dressed in clothing embroidered with fanciful devices; see <hi rend="italic">Camden’s
            Remains</hi>, p. 197, cited in J. R. Planché, <hi rend="italic">History of British
            Costume, from the Earliest</hi><hi rend="italic"> Period to the Close of the Eighteenth
            Century</hi> (London: George Bell and Sons, 1874), pp. 178, 179–80. An unmarried
          daughter could be represented as bearing the paternal arms. In a miniature in the Luttrell
          Psalter, fol. 202v (c. 1325–35), Agnes Sutton and Beatrice Scrope are both represented in
          heraldic gowns showing the signs of their husband and father, respectively; see <hi
            rend="italic">Age of Chivalry: Art in Plantagenet England, 1200</hi><hi rend="italic"
            >–1400</hi>, ed. Jonathan Alexander and Paul Binski (London: Royal Academy of Arts,
          1987), p. 58. See also the fifteenth-century stained-glass portraits in Long Melford
          Church, where the dresses of the Clopton women are decorated with both the paternal and
          marital coats of arms (<hi rend="italic">Mapping Margery Kempe</hi>, <ref
            target="http://www.holycross.edu/kempe" type="external"
            >http://www.holycross.edu/kempe</ref>, s.v., Parish and Cathedral). On heraldic badges,
          see Lightbown, pp. 196–201.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="47">201<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">wot and wene</hi>.
          Verse tag. See line 47.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="48">210<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">here-leke</hi>. MS:
            <hi rend="italic">lere</hi><hi rend="italic"> leke</hi>. I agree with Gor, who reads as
            <hi rend="italic">here leke</hi>, “her hair enclosed her.” H reads <hi rend="italic"
            >lere leke</hi> as “face-radiance, radiance of countenance”; G reads <hi rend="italic"
            >here </hi><hi rend="italic">heke</hi>; A, AW, and V read <hi rend="italic"
            >lere-leke</hi> as “wimple,” lit. “face-linen.” Since the stanza emphasizes her unbound
          hair and lovely complexion, she would have been unlikely to be wearing a wimple. The
          description is evocative of late medieval depictions of the virgin martyrs, who rarely
          wear face linen and most often have unbound hair. For images, see Karen Winstead, <hi
            rend="italic">Virgin Martyrs: Legends of Sainthood in </hi><hi rend="italic">Late
            Medieval England</hi> (Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 1997).</note>
        <note type="enote" n="49">215<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">depe </hi><hi
            rend="italic">colour</hi>. A, AW, and Gor translate as “glowing whiteness” (G as
          “glowing beauty”), whereas H and V follow A. S. Cook, “<hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>,
          212ff,” <hi rend="italic">Modern Philology</hi> 6 (1908), 197, who argues that <hi
            rend="italic">depe colour</hi> stands for “wide collar.” “Collar” follows the logic of
          the top-to-toe description and makes sense of “porfyl,” “embroidered border,” in line
          216.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="50">233<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">nerre then aunte
            </hi><hi rend="italic">or nece</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Nerre</hi> can imply either
          location or relationship, as in contemporary usage, though the sense here is clearly
          filiative.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="51">235<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">spyce</hi>. G, Gor,
          and H emend to <hi rend="italic">spece</hi>, “person.” As V notes, emendation is
          unnecessary, since <hi rend="italic">e</hi> is a normal variant with <hi rend="italic"
            >i</hi> (<hi rend="italic">y</hi>). <hi rend="italic">Spyce</hi> also means “spice
          plant,” certainly within the metaphoric register of the poem, especially since in stanzas
          2 and 3 the poet describes how the spice plants of the “erber” are fertilized by the decay
          of the girl’s body.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="52">236<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">wommon lore</hi>.
          Editors have translated <hi rend="italic">wommon lore</hi> as “woman’s way” or “in womanly
          fashion.” By far the commonest uses of <hi rend="italic">lore</hi> in Middle English
          concern teaching, instruction, or doctrine. <hi rend="italic">MED</hi>, sense 2a, offers
          examples of the possessive; e.g., Chaucer’s “Christes lore” (The General Prologue to <hi
            rend="italic">The Canterbury Tales</hi>, line 527). <hi rend="italic">Lore</hi> as
          “counsel” follows logically from her speaking in the preceding line.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="53">245<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">aglyghte</hi>. A, AW,
          Gor, and V translate as “slipped away,” G as “glided,” but I prefer H’s more literal
          “glittered away,” in keeping with the kinetic and lapidary imaging of loss throughout the
          poem.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="54">250<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">daunger</hi>. See line
          11, and note on <hi rend="italic">luf</hi><hi rend="italic">-daungere</hi>.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="55">254<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">graye</hi>. The eyes
          of beautiful women are conventionally described as gray in English courtly love
          poetry.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="56">259<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">cofer</hi>. Usually a
          “strong box for storage of valuables,” but also with secondary meaning of “coffin.”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="57">260<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">gracios </hi><hi
            rend="italic">gaye</hi>. AW read <hi rend="italic">gracios gay</hi> as an adjective
          modifying garden: “charmingly fair garden.” <hi rend="italic">Gracios gaye</hi> may also
          mean “gracious fair one,” as in line 189. The grammatical construction is
          ambiguous.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="58">271<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">kynde of the
            kyste</hi>. The maiden speaks enigmatically of roses, chests, and pearls to introduce
          ideas of death and transfiguration. <hi rend="italic">Kyste</hi> can also suggest a
          reliquary.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="59">274<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">oght of noght</hi>.
          I.e., has made a pearl out of an ephemeral rose.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="60">277<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">geste</hi>. The <hi
            rend="italic">MED</hi> cites this line for <hi rend="italic">geste</hi> as “one newly
          arrived in a place.” The meaning of <hi rend="italic">gesta</hi>, “story, tale,” which
          alliterates with <hi rend="italic">juel</hi>, may also pertain.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="61">283<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">ma </hi><hi
            rend="italic">feste</hi>. “Make a festival,” i.e., “make merry.”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="62">307<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">westernays</hi>. For a
          summary of the debate on this term, see V. <hi rend="italic">Westernays</hi> does not
          appear elsewhere in Middle English, and may be the poet’s neologism from OF <hi
            rend="italic">bestorner</hi>, e.g., “wrongly turned,” as when a church faces west rather
          than east.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="63">312<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">dem</hi>. G emends to
            <hi rend="italic">deme</hi>. The link word of this stanza group, <hi rend="italic"
            >dem</hi> covers a broad range of actions under the general rubric “judge,” from God’s
          judgment to human acts of evaluation, consideration, and critique.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="64">345<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">daunce as any do</hi>.
          The image is a hunting metaphor and describes the agonal moment.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="65">351<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">mendes</hi>. H
          translates as “opinions,” taking <hi rend="italic">mendes</hi> as a variant for <hi
            rend="italic">mynde</hi>: “Your opinions mount to not a mite.” V translates after <hi
            rend="italic">OED</hi>
          <hi rend="italic">mend</hi>, sb., sense 2, “remedy.”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="66">359<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">mythe</hi>. As V
          notes, most editors have read <hi rend="italic">mythe</hi> as “conceal.” <hi rend="italic"
            >Mythe</hi> from Middle English <hi rend="italic">mouthen</hi>, “to say, speak,
          pronounce,” and hence “mutter” or even “mouth off,” is more consistent with the thought of
          the stanza.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="67">365<space rend="indent1"/>Early editors joined lines 365 and 366,
          “as water gushing from a stream / I put myself at his mercy,” but following the suggestion
          by Gor I have joined lines 364–65: “my heart was afflicted with loss / As water welling
          from a spring.” Although water flowing from a spring would be expected to be redemptive
          (baptismal waters), the irruptive emotions in this stanza are all on the side of grief.
          Hence the image of spring-water is ironically placed — on the side of grief but belonging
          properly to consolation.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="68">368<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">forloyne</hi>. A
          hunting term to describe when dogs race ahead too fast and lose the pack; see Ad Putter,
          “The Ways and Words of the Hunt: Notes on <hi rend="italic">Sir</hi><hi rend="italic">
            Gawain and the Green Knight</hi>, <hi rend="italic">The Master of Game</hi>, <hi
            rend="italic">Sir</hi><hi rend="italic"> Tristrem</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>,
          and <hi rend="italic">Saint Erkenwald</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Chaucer Review</hi> 40
          (2006), 354–85, at 373.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="69"><space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">endorde</hi>. G reads
          “adored one,” but as AW note, Gert Rønberg, “A Note on ‘Endorde’ in <hi rend="italic"
            >Pearl</hi> (368),” <hi rend="italic">English Studies</hi> 57 (1976), 198, argues that
          it is from OF <hi rend="italic">endorer</hi>, “to invest with gold or a gold-like
          quality.”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="70">375<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">wothe</hi>. G reads
          “path,” H reads “search,” and other editors “dangers.” My reading follows G’s “path” from
          OE <hi rend="italic">wath</hi>, “hunting ground, hence generically, place.”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="71">380<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">by stok other
            ston</hi>. As H notes, this common phrase in alliterative poetry can also be a mild
          oath.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="72">385<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">blent</hi>. I.e.,
          “blended in bliss,” “set in joy.”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="73">395<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">hyghe gate</hi>. Most
          editors have read as “highway,” after <hi rend="italic">OED</hi>
          <hi rend="italic">gate</hi>, sense 1b, which gives the line as an example of the meaning
          of <hi rend="italic">gate</hi> as road: “the highway of all my joy.” The more common
          meaning of <hi rend="italic">gate</hi> in Middle English is the modern sense; that meaning
          may pertain as well — e.g., the main gate, a reading that evokes the gates of the New
          Jerusalem in lines 1034 ff.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="74">407<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">My Lorde the
          Lamb</hi>. This is the first of many references to Christ as the Lamb of God.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="75">410<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">stage</hi>. G glosses
          as “degree of advancement,” after <hi rend="italic">OED</hi>
          <hi rend="italic">stage</hi> sb., sense 3. The attention to hierarchical ordering
          anticipates the dreamer’s intellectual and emotional crisis concerning the Pearl’s place
          in the hierarchy of heaven, as V notes.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="76">416<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">wage</hi>. G argues
          that <hi rend="italic">wage</hi> must come from French “wager,” and here must be used in
          the sense of “to be assured.” Gor emphasizes the mercantile in “continue securely” or
          “bring reward,” anticipating the material rhetoric of line 417 and later of the vineyard
          parable.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="77">419<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">pyese</hi>. I accord
          with V who argues that what editors have read as <hi rend="italic">prese</hi>, “value,” is
          in fact <hi rend="italic">pyese</hi>, “maiden,” rendering lines 417–19: “And endowed with
          all His heritage / Is His beloved. I am entirely His, / His maiden, His honored one; and
          His lineage . . .” <hi rend="italic">Pyece</hi> for maiden appears in lines 192 and 229.
          The maiden’s description of her marriage echoes the mystical marriage of St. Katherine in
          the many late medieval versions of the legend. When pressed to marry, Katherine finally
          agrees, but sets the condition that her bridegroom must be the richest, the most
          beautiful, and the most noble (compare <hi rend="italic">parage</hi>, also in line 419)
          man in the world — adding, in some versions, that he also has to be born of a virgin. See
          for example, <hi rend="italic">St. Katherine of Alexandria</hi><hi rend="italic">: The
            Late Middle English Prose Legend in Southwell Minster MS</hi><hi rend="italic"> 7</hi>,
          ed. Saara Nevanlinna and Irma Taavitsainen (Cambridge: D. S. Brewer, 1993), p. 73, and
          Katherine J. Lewis, <hi rend="italic">The Cult</hi><hi rend="italic"> of St. Katherine in
            Late Medieval England</hi> (Woodbridge, Suffolk: Boydell Press, 2000).</note>
        <note type="enote" n="78">430<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Fenyx of Arraby</hi>.
          Christ is often compared to the phoenix, a symbol of rebirth; in this case the phoenix
          represents Mary’s immaculate conception. As G notes, Blanch is compared to the <hi
            rend="italic">Fenix of Arabye</hi> in Chaucer’s <hi rend="italic">Book of the
            Duchess</hi> (lines 980–81).</note>
        <note type="enote" n="79">431<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">freles</hi>. AW follow
          H and emend to <hi rend="italic">fereles</hi>, “without equal,” in keeping with the
          emphasis in the stanza on the Virgin’s uniqueness. “Flawless,” however, is consistent with
          the metaphor of the phoenix as a sign of the immaculate conception.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="80">432<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">quen of
          cortaysye</hi>. I.e., the Virgin Mary.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="81">434<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">folde</hi>. I.e.,
          folds her face in her hands or, as G (also H) suggests, her garment. A, AW, and Gor
          translate as “upturned.”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="82">441<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">emperise</hi>. I.e.,
          Mary the “quen of cortaysye” (line 432).</note>
        <note type="enote" n="83">450<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">fayn of otheres
            hafyng</hi>. The maiden describes heaven as egalitarian and without envy, with each
          queen or king (i.e., saved soul) rejoicing in the <hi rend="italic">hafyng</hi> or
          possessions of the others.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="84">445–52<space rend="indent1"/>Compare <hi rend="italic">The London
            Lapidary of King Philip</hi>: “nyne ordres of angeles that lyven in that joye that noon
          hath envye of othre, that is the life corouned, in the which shal noon entre but he be
          kyng corouned or quene, for all be corouned be name” (<hi rend="italic">English
            Medieval</hi><hi rend="italic"> Lapidaries</hi>, ed. Joan Evans and Mary S. Sargeantson,
          EETS o.s. 190 [London: Oxford University Press, 1933], pp. 19–20, as noted by Robert J.
          Blanch, “Color Symbolism and Mystical Contemplation in <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>,” <hi
            rend="italic">Nottingham Medieval Studies</hi> 17 [1973], 74). See also V.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="85">457<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Saynt Poule</hi>. The
          definition of courtesy that follows is an exposition of St. Paul’s analogy in
          I Corinthians 12:12–31. The image of the corporate body describes the ordering of heaven
          and of the soul as an idealized courtly society, an organism of egalitarian
          hierarchy.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="86">464<space rend="indent1"/>I.e., exists between your limbs.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="87">473<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">over hygh</hi>. The
          dreamer objects to the beatitude of one so young, noting that the same reward is given to
          one who suffers “in penaunce” all his life (line 477).</note>
        <note type="enote" n="88">485<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Pater ne Crede</hi>.
          The dreamer’s point that the <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>-maiden’s two-year sojourn in
          “oure thede” (line 483) was too short to learn the Paternoster (Lord’s Prayer) or Creed
          suggests that she was a child, as most readers have assumed. H suggests that she was a
          novitiate, as does Staley, “<hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> and the Contingencies of Love and
          Piety.” Mother Angela Carson, O.S.U., “Aspects of Elegy in the Middle English <hi
            rend="italic">Pearl</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Studies in Philology</hi> 62 (1965), 17,
          argues that the lines indicate she was a foreigner.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="89">497<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">As </hi><hi
            rend="italic">Mathew meles</hi>. The parable of the vineyard, lines 497–500, is from
          Matthew 20:1–16. The poet’s changes to the biblical source give the parable application to
          fourteenth-century social conditions, and perhaps even specifically to the Statute of
          Laborers of 1388, according to Bowers, “The Politics of <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>”; and
          Watkins.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="90">504<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">dere the date</hi>.
          The time of year is March and the activity is the pruning of vines, as in the March entry
          in the <hi rend="italic">Très Riches </hi><hi rend="italic">Heures</hi> of the Duc de
          Berry. <hi rend="italic">Date</hi> as link-word juxtaposes church time and merchant time;
          see Barr, pp. 71–72.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="91">505<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">hyne</hi>. A, AW, and
          Gor translate as “laborers.” I translate as “households” because the uses of <hi
            rend="italic">hyne</hi> in the poem (lines 632, 1211) refer broadly to members of a
          household or even God’s household, rather than to laborers, as G notes.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="92">512<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">man hit clos</hi>.
          I.e., tie up the pruned vines.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="93">555<space rend="indent1"/>Matthew 20:12 reads: <hi rend="italic"
            >Hi novissimi una hora fecerunt</hi> (“These last have worked but one hour”). This verse
          is paraphrased in line 551, but here <hi rend="italic">houres two</hi> effectively recalls
          that the maiden “lyfed not two yer in oure thede” (line 483), as noted in V.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="94">565–68<space rend="indent1"/>As G notes, these lines paraphrase
          the Vulgate and seem to echo uncannily the Wycliffite Bible, Matthew 20:15: “‘Whether it
          is not leueful to me to do that that Y wole? Whether thin iye is wicked, for Y am
          good?’”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="95">570–72<space rend="indent1"/>These lines paraphrase Matthew
          20:16.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="96">588<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">to-yere</hi>. Most
          editors have translated “this year,” but as G notes, <hi rend="italic">to-yere</hi>
          carries the colloquial sense of “for a long time.”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="97">581–88<space rend="indent1"/>I.e., though she died early, she was
          received fully into heaven.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="98">603<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">inlyche</hi>. Editors,
          except H and V, have translated as “alike, the same.” As V comments, in note to line 546,
          “fully” “suits the interpretation of the parable of the vineyard more exactly, since each
          soul receives ‘fully’ the reward of salvation, even though there are ranks in the
          hierarchical system of heaven.”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="99">609–10<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">dard</hi>. The word
          may derive from OE <hi rend="italic">darian</hi>, “lurk in dread,” or from OE <hi
            rend="italic">durran</hi>, “dare,” as Gor notes in a comment on the difficulty of these
          lines. Most editors have followed G in rendering “His privilege is great who always stood
          in awe / Of Him who brings salvation from sin.” My reading accords with AW, “His (God’s)
          generosity is great (or abundant): those who at any time in their lives submitted to Him
          who rescues sinners — from them no bliss will be withheld.”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="100">617<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">bourne abate</hi>.
          The sense of the maiden’s argument here is that everybody sins and forfeits heaven, but
          God’s grace can save them.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="101">635<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">fyne</hi>. Most
          readers have read as adverb, “at the first in full.” I accord with the suggestion by
          Carter Revard, “A Note on ‘at the fyrst fyne’ (<hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> 635),” <hi
            rend="italic">English Language Notes</hi> 1 (1964), 164–66, who interprets <hi
            rend="italic">fyne</hi> as a noun according to <hi rend="italic">MED</hi> senses 6–11
          (legal terms related to contracts) and translates “as according to the original
          contract.”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="102">652<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">deth secounde</hi>.
          The first redemption over death, determined by Adam’s fall, is baptism; the second is in
          Christ’s resurrection.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="103">674<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">God</hi>. A, G, and
          Gor interpret this as “good,” but, following suggestion by H, other editors, myself as
          well, have read as <hi rend="italic">God</hi>.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="104">677<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Sauter</hi>. A
          Psalter, or collection of the psalms. Collections of the psalms were among the few prayer
          books normally owned by the laity; the term “psalter” could also mean a book of hours or a
          type of compilation prayer book commonly owned by non-clerical or lay people, often
          exquisitely illuminated. Many were owned by women. The passage paraphrases Psalm 14:1–3 or
          Psalm 23:3, 4. For the history and use of books of hours, see John Harthan, <hi
            rend="italic">Books of Hours</hi><hi rend="italic"> and Their Owners</hi> (London:
          Thames and Hudson, 1982).</note>
        <note type="enote" n="105">689<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">sas</hi>. G, Gor, H,
          and V translate word as “sees,” but “says” makes far more sense with the biblical source.
          AW emend to <hi rend="italic">sayz</hi>, a change that, as V shows, is not
          necessary.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="106">691<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">he</hi>. Gor and H
          emend to <hi rend="italic">ho</hi>, i.e., “wisdom,” a female personification. As G notes,
          Wisdom would have suggested Christ to a medieval reader; hence the pronoun <hi
            rend="italic">he</hi> to indicate Wisdom as Christ.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="107">697–700<space rend="indent1"/>See Psalm 142:2.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="108">703<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Allege</hi>. Early
          editors read <hi rend="italic">allege</hi> as an imperative, “renounce your claim.”
          Following Gor, editors have read <hi rend="italic">allege</hi> as conditional subjunctive,
          “if you plead,” i.e., “if you try to plead your case before God, you might get trapped by
          the same kind of talk,” entrapment, that is, in legalisms. For use of legal terms, see
          Silar.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="109">721<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Jesu</hi>. This line
          is the only place in the poem where the concatenation fails. AW substitute <hi
            rend="italic">ryght</hi> for <hi rend="italic">Jesu</hi>, “justice,” as a
          personification of Jesus.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="110">711–24<space rend="indent1"/>Passage is based on Luke 18:15–17,
          Matthew 19:13–15, and Mark 10:13–16.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="111">733<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">makelles</hi>. G
          emends to <hi rend="italic">maskeles</hi>, and also in line 757, to preserve the
          continuity of the link words. But by alternating <hi rend="italic">makeles</hi> with <hi
            rend="italic">maskeles</hi> the poet plays on the equivalence of spotlessness and
          peerlessness.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="112">735<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">hevenesse clere</hi>.
          G emends to <hi rend="italic">hevenes spere</hi>, “heaven’s sphere,” to avoid repeating
            <hi rend="italic">clere</hi> as rhyming word twice in one stanza. H and V translate as
          “heaven’s brightness,” whereas other editors, and myself, translate <hi rend="italic"
            >clere</hi> as an adjective modifying the noun <hi rend="italic">hevenesse</hi>,
          “heaven.”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="113">730–35<space rend="indent1"/>The story of the pearl of price
          comes from Matthew 13:45–46.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="114">740<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">stode</hi>. V accords
          with G in reading <hi rend="italic">stode</hi> as a noun meaning “place”: <hi
            rend="italic">hit stode</hi>, “its place.” Other editors, myself included, understand
            <hi rend="italic">stode</hi> as a verb meaning either “stood” or “shone.” <hi
            rend="italic">Stode</hi>, which appears frequently in the MS, almost always is in the
          form of the verb. One possible meaning of the term as noun, however, is <hi rend="italic"
            >MED</hi> sense 4, s.v., <hi rend="italic">stod</hi>, “an ornamental boss on a
          garment.”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="115">750<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Pymalyon
          paynted</hi>. The contrast between the work of nature and of art is conventional; see <hi
            rend="italic">Le Roman </hi><hi rend="italic">de la Rose</hi>, 16013 ff. As Ovid tells
          the story, Pygmalion carved an image of a beautiful woman and then fell in love with it.
          The story was often used in the Middle Ages to signify the seductions of art and idolatry.
          For discussion and illustrations, see Michael Camille, <hi rend="italic">The </hi><hi
            rend="italic">Gothic Idol: Ideology and Image-Making in Medieval Art</hi> (Cambridge:
          Cambridge University Press, 1991), pp. 316–38; and D. W. Robertson, Jr., <hi rend="italic"
            >A Preface to Chaucer: Studies in Medieval Perspectives</hi> (Princeton: Princeton
          University Press, 1969), pp. 99–103, 157–58. Chaucer uses the trope as a debate between
          art and nature in The Physician’s Tale, lines 8–38.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="116">755<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">ostriys</hi>. The
          reading of this word has been the subject of a long debate. G emends to <hi rend="italic"
            >of triys</hi>, “of peace, truce.” Gor reads the word as <hi rend="italic">offys</hi>,
          “office,” a reading that has been followed by subsequent editors; so too AW, A, and C. The
          issues over interpretation are based on the central letters of the word: are they <hi
            rend="italic">ff</hi> or <hi rend="italic">st</hi> followed by a scribal abbreviation
          for <hi rend="italic">ri</hi>? My vote for “oyster” has been swayed by the argument of E.
          T. Donaldson that <hi rend="italic">ostriys</hi> is acceptable on orthographic, syntactic,
          and textual/symbolic grounds; “Oysters, Forsooth: Two Readings in <hi rend="italic"
            >Pearl</hi>,” in <hi rend="italic">Studies Presented to Tauno</hi><hi rend="italic"> F.
            Mustanoja on the Occasion of His Sixtieth Birthday</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
            >Neuphilologische</hi><hi rend="italic"> Mitteilungen</hi> 73 (1972), 75–82. While the
          abbreviation mark indicating <hi rend="italic">ri</hi> could possibly be read as the top
          of an <hi rend="italic">f</hi> that missed its connection with the stroke, as Davis argues
          in his defense of a reading of the term as <hi rend="italic">offys</hi> (Norman Davis,
          review of Gordon’s edition of <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Medium
            Aevum</hi> 23 [1954], 98–99), the word presents in the MS very clearly, and the letter
          in question is unlike <hi rend="italic">f</hi> as written elsewhere in the MS. V says that
          “the tops of f’s are not always securely joined in the MS” — but the example he gives, <hi
            rend="italic">of</hi> in line 752, is not convincing, for in that example the top is
          much closer to the stroke.<p style="enote-indent">“Oyster,” which can be derived without
            emendation, can also be defended on textual grounds. As Donaldson argues, introducing an
            oyster at this point in the poem would be entirely what one might expect of both poet
            and dreamer. This stanza in particular is remarkable for its density of metaphor, full
            of supposition and grounded in localizing particulars as the dreamer asks the pearl who
            formed her and what bears her. In medieval natural history, pearls were believed to be
            produced from dew drops swallowed by the oyster, a belief that contributed to the rich
            symbolism of pearls. See Donkin, pp. 1–22.</p></note>
        <note type="enote" n="117">761<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">wete</hi>. I accord
          with A, AW, G, and Gor who translate as “wet,” e.g., “dismal” — a characterization of the
          world that also perhaps answers, tongue-in-cheek, the narrator’s question about her origin
          as oyster. Other editors have proposed very different translations: H reads as noun,
          “woe,” and V the very plausible adjective “mad,” derived from <hi rend="italic">wede</hi>,
          “to go insane.”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="118">763<space rend="indent1"/>The language is from the Song of Songs
          4:7–8: <hi rend="italic">Tota pulchra es, </hi><hi rend="italic">amica mea, et macula non
            est in te. Veni de </hi><hi rend="italic">Libano, sponsa mea . . .</hi> (“You are fair,
          my love, there is no flaw in you. Come with me from Lebanon, my bride . . . ”). The verse
          was widely used in medieval literature, and in both sacred and fully profane
          contexts.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="119">769<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">bryd</hi>. Both
          meanings of “bride” and “bird” are implied. The use of <hi rend="italic">bryd</hi>,
          “bird,” for a girl is conventional in Middle English love poetry.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="120">776<space rend="indent1"/>I.e., have lived in much strife as
          virgin martyrs, as suggested by Morton Bloomfield, “Some Notes on <hi rend="italic">Sir
            Gawain and the</hi><hi rend="italic"> Green Knight</hi> (lines 374, 546, 752, 1236) and
            <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> (lines 1–12, 61, 775–776, 968),” in <hi rend="italic"
            >Studies in</hi><hi rend="italic"> Language, Literature, and Culture of the Middle Ages
            and Later</hi><hi rend="italic">: Studies in Honor of Rudolph Willard</hi>, ed. E. Bagby
          Atwood and Archibald A. Hill (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1969), p. 302; or as
          “career virgins,” as argued by Watson, in Brewer and Gibson, p. 302. For virgin martyrs,
          see Karen A. Winstead, <hi rend="italic">Virgin Martyrs: Legends of Sainthood </hi><hi
            rend="italic">in Late Medieval England</hi> (Ithaca: Cornell University Press,
          1997).</note>
        <note type="enote" n="121">792<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">The nwe cyté o
            Jerusalem</hi>. This is the first of many references to the New Jerusalem, references
          that increase in intensity up to the climactic or chthonic moment when the dreamer sees
          the Lamb in the middle of the city. Representations of the New Jerusalem, the mystical and
          heavenly city as distinct from the material city of “Jerusalem, Jordan, and Galalye” (line
          817) that the maiden describes in the next stanzas (lines 793–840) appear in illustrations
          of the Book of Revelation (Apocalypse). Illuminated manuscripts of the Apocalypse were
          popular items among wealthy patrons in the high and late Middle Ages. See Introduction,
          pp. 15–17; on political appropriations of Apocalypse imagery in late medieval England, see
          Bowers, “<hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> in Its Royal Setting.”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="122">805–06<space rend="indent1"/>Jesus’ scourging and carrying of the
          Cross to Calvary were popular subjects, illustrated widely in English panel painting and
          alabasters and described in countless ways in lyrics, in devotional literature, and in the
          medieval drama. A powerful dramatization of the nailing of Christ to the Cross appears in
          the York <hi rend="italic">Crucifixion</hi>.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="123">811<space rend="indent1"/>I.e., “for the sake of sin He set His
          own life as totally unimportant.”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="124">818<space rend="indent1"/>According to the Gospels John baptized
          in Jordan, not in Jerusalem and Galilee.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="125">819<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Ysaye</hi>. See
          Isaiah 53:7, where Christ’s silence before his accusers is prophesied.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="126">824<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">upon</hi>. V reads as
          adverb, “openly,” but most editors follow G, who has made a more convincing case for <hi
            rend="italic">upon</hi> as a “preposition placed after the pronoun it governs,” “upon
          that,” i.e., “at which all this world has worked,” or colloquially, “that all this world
          has committed.”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="127">829<space rend="indent1"/>From this point until the last stanza
          group much of the imagery and language is taken from the Book of Revelation.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="128">829–30<space rend="indent1"/>I.e., was perceived as a lamb by
          “ayther prophete” (line 831), both John the Baptist and Isaiah, as named in lines
          819–20.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="129">833<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi
            rend="italic"> thryde tyme</hi>. I.e., first by Isaiah (53:7), then by John the Baptist,
          then (the third time) by St. John the Evangelist (Revelation 5:6).</note>
        <note type="enote" n="130">837<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">leves sware</hi>. In
          Revelation John reads a scroll. <hi rend="italic">Leves sware</hi> suggest he reads a
          book, as Gor notes.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="131">841<space rend="indent1"/>This stanza group contains six stanzas,
          unlike the five stanzas in each of the other nineteen stanza-groups. The additional
          stanza, which brings the total lines of the poem to 1212, furthers the play on the number
          twelve throughout the text: twelve lines per stanza, twelve gem-like foundation layers of
          the New Jerusalem (lines 993–1021); twelve degrees of the New Jerusalem (lines 1021–32);
          twelve gates of the New Jerusalem (line 1035). See Introduction, p. 5, and Peck, pp.
          15–64. Peck, pp. 44–51, considers structural and symbolic uses of 12 in <hi rend="italic"
            >Pearl</hi>.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="132"><space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">pechche</hi>. Most
          editors translate as “stain.” My reading as “patch” accords with G, H, and V.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="133">869<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">maydennes</hi>. In
          his biblical commentary, widely read in the fourteenth century, Augustine glosses
          “maidens” to mean virgins generically — i.e., either female or male, as AW note. In the
          Latin Vulgate Bible, however, “virgins” are explicitly male — i.e., “they who were not
          polluted by women.” For virginity in the Middle Ages see Barbara Newman, <hi rend="italic"
            >From</hi><hi rend="italic"> Virile Woman to WomanChrist: Studies in Medieval Religion
            and Literature</hi> (Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 1995), pp. 28–35.
          Although <hi rend="italic">mayden</hi> may designate a male who has abstained from sex, it
          is a common term in Middle English love poetry, and the person named as such is almost
          invariably female. For the virginity tradition and <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>, see
          Watson, in Brewer and Gibson, p. 301.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="134">873–75<space rend="indent1"/>The destructive scenes of the Book
          of Revelation are not evoked in <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>. These lines alone convey
          something of the sense of destruction, or at least natural forces at work, so common in
          many medieval visual renderings of the Book of Revelation, from illuminated apocalypse
          manuscripts to tympani, carved scenes over doorways, on medieval parishes and cathedrals.
          See Introduction, pp. 15–17. For a richly illustrated introduction to the topic, see
          Jonathan Alexander, with Michael Michael and Martin Kauffmann, “The Last Things:
          Representing the Unrepresentable,” in <hi rend="italic">The Apocalypse and the Shape of
            </hi><hi rend="italic">Things to Come</hi>, ed. Frances Carey (London: British Museum
          Press, 1999), pp. 43–98.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="135">886–87<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">fowre bestes . . .
            aldermen</hi>. The four beasts are the Evangelists, represented in medieval iconography
          as lion (Mark), ox (Luke), eagle (John), and man (Matthew). <hi rend="italic"
            >Aldermen</hi> doubtless signifies the twenty-four elders. Scenes representing God
          enthroned and surrounded by the four evangelists and by elders with musical instruments
          appear frequently in illuminated Apocalypse manuscripts. For the biblical sources for the
          imaging of beasts, elders, and enthroned God, see Revelation 4:4, 7, and Ezekiel 1. The
          term <hi rend="italic">aldermen</hi> may give this description a particularly familiar and
          urban cast. A chronicle entry for 1392 recounts that the Mayor of London was summoned with
          “24 aldermannis” (among others) to a council with the king; <hi rend="italic">Knighton’s
            Chronicle 1337</hi><hi rend="italic">–1396</hi>, ed. and trans. G. H. Martin (Oxford:
          Clarendon Press, 1995), p. 544.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="136">892<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">meyny</hi>. Used here
          as in lines 899 and 960, <hi rend="italic">meyny</hi> describes a lord’s retinue in terms
          consistent with late fourteenth-century aristocratic practice.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="137"><space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">swe</hi>. Probably from
            <hi rend="italic">sue</hi>, “follow,” but perhaps from <hi rend="italic">sough</hi> and
          meaning “the swell of praise,” in keeping with the emphasis on music and sound.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="138">894<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">newe fryt</hi>.
          Compare the fruits in the transformed garden at the beginning of the poem, lines 87 and
          104.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="139">895<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">hit</hi>. I.e., the
          “meyny” or “retinue” of virgins singing in praise of and in likeness to the Lamb.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="140">896<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">lote</hi>. The word
          may signify either voice or appearance, as may <hi rend="italic">hwe</hi>; compare line
          873, where “hue” refers to the cry sounded in heaven. The evocation of sound is consistent
          with the emphasis on voice and melody in these stanzas. Editors translate <hi
            rend="italic">hwe</hi> as “hue” (color); I prefer “sound” in keeping with references to
          song earlier in the stanza.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="141">865–900<space rend="indent1"/>See Revelation 14:1–5 for biblical
          source.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="142">905<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">mokke and mul</hi>.
            <hi rend="italic">Mul</hi>, “dust” or “mud,” recalls “moul” of line 23, and here
          specifically suggests the difference in social class between the pearl and himself. As
          Barr notes, mud is often used in medieval texts to designate peasants (pp. 60,
          74n17).</note>
        <note type="enote" n="143">920<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">David</hi>. David was
          the conqueror of Jerusalem and second king of Israel, 1000–962 BCE.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="144">922<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">note</hi>. A term
          that suggests both a dazzling undertaking as well as musical sound. As Osgood points out,
          in St. Erkenwald the new building of St. Paul’s is also “a noble note.”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="145">923<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">under mone</hi>.
          I.e., on earth. The phrase also implies a contrast between the maiden’s spotlessness and
          the changeable nature of the moon — its spottiness: see line 1070.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="146">925<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">moteles meyny</hi>. A
          pun on “homeless” and “spotless,” evoking the similarly uneasy pun developed in the uses
          of “spot” in the first stanza group.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="147">943<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">nwe</hi>. <hi
            rend="italic">Nwe</hi> may refer to the new law (Christianity) or to the new Jerusalem.
          The maiden explains that the literal Jerusalem is the city of the old law, remade
          figuratively as the new or heavenly Jerusalem through the crucifixion, the event enacting
          the new law — i.e., that humans can win eternal life.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="148"><space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">sonde</hi>. <hi
            rend="italic">Sonde</hi> may alternatively be read as a noun, as in AW and V who
          translate <hi rend="italic">sonde</hi> as “embassy” and “dispensation”: “but the new, that
          descended by God’s embassy.”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="149">952<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Ceté of God</hi>.
          Used in the Old Testament and in biblical exegesis to denote both old and new
          Jerusalems.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="150"><space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Syght of Pes</hi>. Also
            <hi rend="italic">visio pacis</hi>; denotes more directly the new or heavenly
          city.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="151">953<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">at ene</hi>. Editors
          translate variously: G and H as “formerly”; A, AW and Gor as “was made secure”; V as
          “immediately.”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="152">967<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">aquylde</hi>. Editors
          translate variously: AW as “obtained permission” and V as “prevailed upon.” S.v., <hi
            rend="italic">aquylde</hi>
          <hi rend="italic">MED</hi> gives “obtain” as well as “flush, track, pursue,” meanings that
          continue a pattern of hunting references that appears throughout the poem, e.g., lines 184
          and 345.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="153">969<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">cloystor</hi>.
          “Cloister,” “enclosure,” as metonym for “city,” but with sense of enclosure, emphasizing
          the idea that heaven is an ideal cloister.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="154">970<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">fote</hi>. Editors
          have differed on whether we are to take <hi rend="italic">fote</hi> as a measure of
          distance or as the body part. Its placement as final word in the line leaves both
          possibilities in play.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="155">979–81<space rend="indent1"/>In Revelation 21:10. John is taken
          by the angel to a mountain, where he sees the city descending from heaven.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="156">999<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Jasper</hi>. As AW
          and Gor note, not the modern jasper, but a brightly colored and especially green
          chalcedony.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="157">1003<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">calsydoyne</hi>.
          Probably a kind of white quartz. See note in Gor.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="158">1012<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">twynne-hew</hi>. MS:
            <hi rend="italic">twy</hi><hi rend="italic">n̄</hi><hi rend="italic">e how</hi> (<hi
            rend="italic">twynne </hi><hi rend="italic">how</hi>). A, AW, and Gor emend to <hi
            rend="italic">twynne-hew</hi>. As notes in G and Gor explain, the twin-hue of the topaz
          may derive from the lapidaries or from a commentary on the Apocalypse, such as Bede
          (Migne, PL 93.200): <hi rend="italic">topasius . . . duos habere fertur colores; unum auri
            purissimi, et alterum </hi><hi rend="italic">aetherea claritate relucentem</hi> [topaz .
          . . is said to have two colors; one of the purest gold, and the other reflecting ethereal
          clarity].</note>
        <note type="enote" n="159">994–1020<space rend="indent1"/>The natural and mystical
          properties of each of these stones are detailed in medieval lapidaries; see Robert J.
          Blanch, “Precious Metal and Gem Symbolism in <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>,” in <hi
            rend="italic">Sir Gawain and Pearl: Critical Essays</hi>, ed. Robert J. Blanch, pp.
          86–97; and Riddy, in Brewer and Gibson, pp. 143–55. Except for the ruby of line 1007, the
          catalogue follows closely the account in Revelation 21.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="160">1027<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">wones wythinne</hi>.
          As G notes, Revelation 21 says nothing of dwellings within the city.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="161">1030<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Twelve
          forlonge</hi>. Revelation 21:16 has 12,000 furlongs. G omits <hi rend="italic">space</hi>
          and adds <hi rend="italic">thousande</hi>. He is probably correct that 12 represents a
          scribal error and that the line was somehow initially rendered to convey 12,000, in
          keeping with the biblical source. Charles Moorman, however, argues that 12 furlongs
          accords with the dimensions of a medieval manor, “manayre” (line 1029). See “Some Notes on
            <hi rend="italic">Patience</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi>,” <hi rend="italic"
            >Southern Quarterly</hi> 4 (1965), 72–73. Revelation 21 also makes no mention of “wones
          wythinne” (line 1027), a detail added to both familiarize and domesticate the New
          Jerusalem.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="162">1032<space rend="indent1"/>I.e., measured by the angel with the
          measuring rod of Ezekiel 40–44.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="163">1041<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">byrth-whates</hi>. G
          emends to <hi rend="italic">byrthe-whates</hi>. The idea that the names of the children of
          Israel are written on the gates of the city derives from Revelation 21:12; that they
          appear according to the order of their birth, from Exodus 28.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="164">1052<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">apparaylmente</hi>.
          The term likely refers to the elders and evangelists, as H argues, as the maiden has
          described in lines 885–87.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="165">1058<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">flet</hi>. Editors
          have translated variously as “tidal estuary” (V) and as the verb “flowed” (H). <hi
            rend="italic">Flet</hi>, from “floor, ground” accords most closely with the sense of the
          source in Revelation: “flowing from the throne of God,” a scene depicted in some
          illuminated manuscripts, i.e., the Trinity College Apocalypse, which shows the river
          flowing out of the room in which God is enthroned. See the illustration in Jonathan
          Alexander, “The Last Things: Representing the Unrepresentable,” in <hi rend="italic"
            >The</hi><hi rend="italic"> Apocalypse and the Shape of Things to Come</hi>, ed. Frances
          Carey, p. 77.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="166">1069 ff.<space rend="indent1"/>The stanza describes the
          miraculous, God-generated light of the New Jerusalem, a brilliance that eclipses other
          celestial bodies, i.e., moon and sun.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="167">1077–80<space rend="indent1"/>See Revelation 22:2.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="168">1093<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">maynful</hi>.
          Compare the expression “might and main,” in Middle English a conventional formula, “myghty
          and maynful.”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="169">1099<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">vergynes</hi>. See
          note to line 869.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="170">1098–1100<space rend="indent1"/>See Revelation 14:4.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="171">1106<space rend="indent1"/>See Revelation 21:21.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="172">1107<space rend="indent1"/>See Revelation 5:11.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="173">1108<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">livrés</hi>. G
          emends to <hi rend="italic">livre</hi>. Most editors translate as “dress.” <hi
            rend="italic">Livrés</hi> also means the official garb of a group or guild, which would
          seem to be the sense intended here. For a discussion of livery badges in the court of
          Richard II and in the Wilton Diptych, see Riddy, in Brewer and Gibson, p. 153n; Bowers,
            “<hi rend="italic">Pearl</hi> in Its Royal Setting,” pp. 136–39; and Barr, pp. 67–68.
          See also note to line 199.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="174">1110<space rend="indent1"/>See Revelation 14:1–4.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="175">1111<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">golde</hi>. MS: <hi
            rend="italic">glode</hi>. Editors emend. See Revelation 5:6.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="176">1126<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Vertues</hi>. One of
          the nine orders of angels.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="177">1135<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">wounde ful
          wyde</hi>. The image is of the sacrificial Lamb, Christ crucified. Field and Whitaker
          discuss the medieval pictorial traditions for the image; for a psychoanalytic reading of
          the wound, see Stanbury, “Feminist Masterplots.”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="178">1156–59<space rend="indent1"/>These lines present many
          possibilities for interpretation. In line 1156, <hi rend="italic">walte</hi> has been read
          as “held, set,” from Middle English <hi rend="italic">wale</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
            >welde</hi>, by A, AW, G, and Gor; as “kept” by C; and as “vexed” by H and V. The <hi
            rend="italic">MED</hi> suggests “chosen,” p. ppl. of <hi rend="italic">walen</hi>, a
          reading with which I concur: i.e., although she has already been claimed or chosen by the
          Lamb, the dreamer still wants to hurl himself into the stream.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="179">1157–59<space rend="indent1"/>G connects <hi rend="italic">fech
            me bur</hi> (line 1158) with the dialect phrase “to take one’s birr,” i.e., to gather
          momentum for a leap, and translates: “Nothing, methought, might hinder me / From fetching
          birr and taking off; / And noght should keep me from the start.” A reads: “I thought that
          nothing might hinder me from gathering my strength and taking possession (of the Maiden)
          for myself.” My reading of the lines approximates that of AW: “I thought that nothing
          could harm me by dealing me a blow and offering obstruction to me.” <hi rend="italic"
            >Bur</hi> appears frequently in <hi rend="italic">Sir Gawain and the Green Knight</hi>
          in the sense of a martial “blow.” This stanza and the following are rich in abrupt
          monosyllabic words conveying suddenness and violence.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="180">1174<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">raxled</hi>. I.e.,
          in the sense of awakening from a swoon.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="181">1205<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">lote</hi>. <hi
            rend="italic">Lote</hi>, Middle English <hi rend="italic">lot</hi>, which some editors
          translate as “experience,” carries connotations of chance or luck. AW note that <hi
            rend="italic">lote</hi> can also mean “speech” or “word”: “I received this word.”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="182">1206<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">enclyin</hi>.
          Editors translate “lying prostrate” — i.e., the dreamer. I accord with V in following <hi
            rend="italic">MED</hi> suggestion that term is an adjective, <hi rend="italic"
            >enclin</hi>, modifying the pearl, “bowed down, humble, submissive.”</note>
        <note type="enote" n="183">1208<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">In Krystes dere
            blessyng and myn</hi>. This phrase appears frequently in addresses from parent to child
          in the late Middle Ages, as observed by Norman Davis, “A Note on <hi rend="italic"
            >Pearl</hi>,” in Conley, ed., pp. 325–34.</note>
        <note type="enote" n="184">1209<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">forme of bred and
            wyn</hi>. I.e., the visual display of the host during the Mass. The phrase, part of the
          prayer at communion, was, as Margaret Aston says, “the laconic lay equivalent for
          transubstantiation in all its complexities.” See <hi rend="italic">Faith and Fire: Popular
            and Unpopular</hi><hi rend="italic"> Religion, 1350–1600</hi> (Rio Grande, Ohio:
          Hambledon Press, 1993), pp. 46–47. For uses of the formula, see also John Mirk’s <hi
            rend="italic">Instructions for Parish Priests</hi>, ed. Edward Peacock, EETS o.s. 31
          (London: Trübner &amp; Co., 1868; Woodbridge, Suffolk: Boydell &amp; Brewer, 1996), p. 8,
          line 246, and p. 291. The formula also appears frequently in fourteenth- and
          fifteenth-century debates about the Eucharistic rite: see for example the “Testimony of
          William Thorpe” in <hi rend="italic">Two Wycliffite Texts: The Sermon of</hi><hi
            rend="italic"> William Taylor 1406: The Testimony of William Thorpe 1407</hi>, ed. Anne
          Hudson, EETS o.s. 301 (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1993), p. 31.<p
            style="enote-indent">Most editors understand <hi rend="italic">That</hi> as a reference
            to Christ. Phillips, p. 479, argues that <hi rend="italic">That</hi> refers to the pearl
            (“hit” of line 1207) and both refer to the Eucharistic wafer.</p></note>
        <note type="enote" n="185">1211<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">homly hyne</hi>. The
          term <hi rend="italic">homly</hi> defies precise translation in modern English. It refers
          literally to the “homely,” to things of the household and private life, with the
          implication that <hi rend="italic">homly hyne</hi> are trustworthy and trusting household
          servants, allied with the lord or head of household in a harmonious hierarchical
          relationship.</note>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
